<?xml-model href="caesarSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
<title>THE COMMENTARIES OF
CAIUS JULIUS CAESAR</title>


<section part="gaul">THE WAR IN GAUL

<book num="1"><heading>BOOK I</heading>

<chapter n="I">I.--All <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> is divided into three parts, one of which the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>
inhabit, the <tribe name="aquitani">Aquitani</tribe> another, those who in their own language are
called <tribe name="gauls">Celts</tribe>, in ours <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, the third. All these differ from each other
in language, customs and laws. The river <place river="garonne">Garonne</place> separates the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>
from the <tribe name="aquitani">Aquitani</tribe>; the <place river="marne">Marne</place> and the <place river="seine">Seine</place> separate them from the
<tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>. Of all these, the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> are the bravest, because they are
farthest from the civilisation and refinement of [our] Province, and
merchants least frequently resort to them and import those things which
tend to effeminate the mind; and they are the nearest to the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>,
who dwell beyond the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, with whom they are continually waging war;
for which reason the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> also surpass the rest of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> in
valour, as they contend with the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> in almost daily battles, when
they either repel them from their own territories, or themselves wage
war on their frontiers. One part of these, which it has been said that
the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> occupy, takes its beginning at the river <place river="rhone">Rhone</place>: it is bounded
by the river <place river="garonne">Garonne</place>, the ocean, and the territories of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>: it
borders, too, on the side of the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> and the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, upon the
river <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, and stretches towards the north. The <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> rise from the
extreme frontier of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, extend to the lower part of the river <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>;
and look towards the north and the rising sun. <place region="aquitania">Aquitania</place> extends from
the river <place river="garonne">Garonne</place> to the <place mountain="pyrenees">Pyrenaean</place> mountains and to that part of the
ocean which is near <place region="spain">Spain</place>: it looks between the setting of the sun and
the north star.</chapter>

<chapter n="II">II.--Among the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, <persName eth="helvetii" role="arist">Orgetorix</persName> was by far the most distinguished and
wealthy. He, when <persName eth="roman" role="consul">Marcus Messala</persName> and <persName eth="roman" role="consul">Marcus Piso</persName> were consuls, incited
by lust of sovereignty, formed a conspiracy among the nobility, and
persuaded the people to go forth from their territories with all their
possessions, [saying] that it would be very easy, since they excelled
all in valour, to acquire the supremacy of the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>. To this he
the more easily persuaded them, because the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> are confined on
every side by the nature of their situation; on one side by the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, a
very broad and deep river, which separates the Helvetian territory from
the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>; on a second side by the <place mountain="jura">Jura</place>, a very high mountain which is
[situated] between the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> and the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>; on a third by the Lake
of <place settlement="geneva">Geneva</place>, and by the river <place river="rhone">Rhone</place>, which separates our Province from the
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>. From these circumstances it resulted that they could range
less widely, and could less easily make war upon their neighbours; for
which reason men fond of war [as they were] were affected with great
regret. They thought, that considering the extent of their population,
and their renown for warfare and bravery, they had but narrow limits,
although they extended in <dimensions>length 240, and in breadth 180 [Roman] miles.</dimensions>
<!-- KYW: dimensions may be useful for building a map, but may end up ignoring --></chapter>

<chapter n="III">III.--Induced by these considerations, and influenced by the authority
of <persName eth="helvetii" role="arist">Orgetorix</persName>, they determined to provide such things as were necessary
for their expedition--to buy up as great a number as possible of beasts
of burden and waggons--to make their sowings as large as possible, so
that on their march plenty of corn might be in store--and to establish
peace and friendship with the neighbouring states. They reckoned that a
term of two years would be sufficient for them to execute their designs;
they fix by decree their departure for the third year. <persName eth="helvetii" role="arist">Orgetorix</persName> is
chosen to complete these arrangements. He took upon himself the office
of ambassador to the states: on this journey he persuades <persName eth="sequani">Casticus</persName>, the
son of <persName eth="sequani">Catamantaledes</persName> (one of the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, whose father had possessed
the sovereignty among the people for many years, and had been styled
"_friend_" by the senate of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>), to seize upon the
sovereignty in his own state, which his father had held before him, and
he likewise persuades <persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName>, an Aeduan, the brother of <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>,
who at that time possessed the chief authority in the state, and was
exceedingly beloved by the people, to attempt the same, and gives him
his daughter in marriage. He proves to them that to accomplish their
attempts was a thing very easy to be done, because he himself would
obtain the government of his own state; that there was no doubt that the
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> were the most powerful of the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>; he assures them
that he will, with his own forces and his own army, acquire the
sovereignty for them. Incited by this speech, they give a pledge and
oath to one another, and hope that, when they have seized the
sovereignty, they will, by means of the three most powerful and valiant
nations, be enabled to obtain possession of the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>.</chapter>

<chapter n="IV">IV.--When this scheme was disclosed to the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> by informers, they,
according to their custom, compelled <persName eth="helvetii" role="arist">Orgetorix</persName> to plead his cause in
chains; it was the law that the penalty of being burned by fire should
await him if condemned. On the day appointed for the pleading of his
cause, <persName eth="helvetii" role="arist">Orgetorix</persName> drew together from all quarters to the court all his
vassals to the number of ten thousand persons; and led together to the
same place, and all his dependants and debtor-bondsmen, of whom he had a
great number; by means of these he rescued himself from [the necessity
of] pleading his cause. While the state, incensed at this act, was
endeavouring to assert its right by arms, and the magistrates were
mustering a large body of men from the country, <persName eth="helvetii" role="arist">Orgetorix</persName> died; and
there is not wanting a suspicion, as the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> think, of his having
committed suicide.</chapter>

<chapter n="V">V.--After his death, the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> nevertheless attempt to do that which
they had resolved on, namely, to go forth from their territories. When
they thought that they were at length prepared for this undertaking,
they set fire to all their towns, in number about twelve--to their
villages about four hundred--and to the private dwellings that remained;
they burn up all the corn, except what they intend to carry with them;
that after destroying the hope of a return home, they might be the more
ready for undergoing all dangers. They order every one to carry forth
from home for himself provisions for three months, ready ground. They
persuade the <tribe name="rauraci">Rauraci</tribe>, and the <tribe name="tulingi">Tulingi</tribe>, and the <tribe name="latobrigi">Latobrigi</tribe>, their
neighbours, to adopt the same plan, and after burning down their towns
and villages, to set out with them: and they admit to their party and
unite to themselves as confederates the <tribe name="boii">Boii</tribe>, who had dwelt on the other
side of the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, and had crossed over into the Norican territory, and
assaulted <place region="noreia">Noreia</place>.</chapter>

<chapter n="VI">VI.--There were in all two routes by which they could go forth from
their country--one through the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, narrow and difficult, between
<place mountain="jura">Mount Jura</place> and the river <place river="rhone">Rhone</place> (by which scarcely one waggon at a time
could be led; there was, moreover, a very high mountain overhanging, so
that a very few might easily intercept them); the other, through our
Province, much easier and freer from obstacles, because the <place river="rhone">Rhone</place> flows
between the boundaries of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> and those of the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>, who
had lately been subdued, and is in some places crossed by a ford. The
furthest town of the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>, and the nearest to the territories of
the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, is <place settlement="geneva">Geneva</place>. From this town a bridge extends to the
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>. They thought that they should either persuade the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>,
because they did not seem as yet well-affected towards the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>,
or compel them by force to allow them to pass through their territories.
Having provided everything for the expedition, they appoint a day on
which they should all meet on the bank of the <place river="rhone">Rhone</place>. This day was the
fifth before the kalends of April [_i.e._ the <date day="BC00580328">28th of March</date>], in the
consulship of <persName eth="roman" role="consul">Lucius Piso</persName> and <persName eth="roman" role="consul">Aulus Gabinius</persName> [B.C. 58].</chapter>


<chapter n="VII">VII.--When it was reported to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> that they were attempting to make
their route through our Province, he hastens to set out from the city,
and, by as great marches as he can, proceeds to Further <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and
arrives at <place settlement="geneva">Geneva</place>. He orders the whole Province [to furnish] as great a
number of soldiers as possible, as there was in all only one legion in
Further <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>: he orders the bridge at <place settlement="geneva">Geneva</place> to be broken down. When the
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> are apprised of his arrival, they send to him, as ambassadors,
the most illustrious men of their state (in which embassy Numeius and
Verudoctius held the chief place), to say "that it was their intention
to march through the Province without doing any harm, because they had"
[according to their own representations] "no other route:--that they
requested they might be allowed to do so with his consent." <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>,
inasmuch as he kept in remembrance that <persName eth="roman" role="consul">Lucius Cassius</persName>, the consul, had
been slain, and his army routed and made to pass under the yoke by the
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, did not think that [their request] ought to be granted; nor
was he of opinion that men of hostile disposition, if an opportunity of
marching through the Province were given them, would abstain from
outrage and mischief. Yet, in order that a period might intervene, until
the soldiers whom he had ordered [to be furnished] should assemble, he
replied to the ambassadors, that he would take time to deliberate; if
they wanted anything, they might return on the day before the ides of
<date day="BC00580412">April [on April 12th]</date>.</chapter>

<chapter n="VIII">VIII.--Meanwhile, with the legion which he had with him and the soldiers
who had assembled from the Province, he carries along for <dimensions>nineteen
[Roman, not quite eighteen English] miles a wall, to the height of
sixteen feet</dimensions>, and a trench, from the lake of <place settlement="geneva">Geneva</place>, which flows into
the river <place river="rhone">Rhone</place>, to <place mountain="jura">Mount Jura</place>, which separates the territories of the
<tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> from those of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>. When that work was finished, he
distributes garrisons, and closely fortifies redoubts, in order that he
may the more easily intercept them, if they should attempt to cross over
against his will. When the day which he had appointed with the
ambassadors came, and they returned to him, he says that he cannot,
consistently with the custom and precedent of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, grant
any one a passage through the Province; and he gives them to understand
that, if they should attempt to use violence, he would oppose them. The
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, disappointed in this hope, tried if they could force a passage
(some by means of a bridge of boats and numerous rafts constructed for
the purpose; others, by the fords of the <place river="rhone">Rhone</place>, where the depth of the
river was least, sometimes by day, but more frequently by night), but
being kept at bay by the strength of our works, and by the concourse of
the soldiers, and by the missiles, they desisted from this attempt.</chapter>

<chapter n="IX">IX.--There was left one way, [namely] through the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, by which, on
account of its narrowness, they could not pass without the consent of
the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>. As they could not of themselves prevail on them, they send
ambassadors to <persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName> the Aeduan, that through his intercession they
might obtain their request from the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>. <persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName>, by his popularity
and liberality, had great influence among the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, and was friendly
to the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, because out of that state he had married the daughter
of <persName eth="helvetii" role="arist">Orgetorix</persName>; and, incited by lust of sovereignty, was anxious for a
revolution, and wished to have as many states as possible attached to
him by his kindness towards them. He, therefore, undertakes the affair,
and prevails upon the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> to allow the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> to march through
their territories, and arranges that they should give hostages to each
other--the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> not to obstruct the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> in their march--the
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, to pass without mischief and outrage.</chapter>

<chapter n="X">X.--It-is again told <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> that the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> intend to march through
the country of the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> and the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> into the territories of the
Santones, which are not far distant from those boundaries of the
Tolosates, which [viz. Tolosa, Toulouse] is a state in the Province. If
this took place, he saw that it would be attended with great danger to
the Province to have warlike men, enemies of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, bordering
upon an open and very fertile tract of country. For these reasons he
appointed <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName>, his lieutenant, to the command of the
fortification which he had made. He himself proceeds to <place region="italy">Italy</place> by forced
marches, and there levies two legions, and leads out from winter-quarters
three which were wintering around Aquileia, and with these five
legions marches rapidly by the nearest route across the <place mountain="Alps">Alps</place> into
Further <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>. Here the Centrones and the Graioceli and the Caturiges,
having taken possession of the higher parts, attempt to obstruct the
army in their march. After having routed these in several battles, he
arrives in the territories of the <tribe name="Vocontii">Vocontii</tribe> in the Further Province on
the seventh day from Ocelum, which is the most remote town of the Hither
Province; thence he leads his army into the country of the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>,
and from the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe> to the Segusiani. These people are the first
beyond the Province on the opposite side of the <place river="rhone">Rhone</place>.</chapter>

<chapter n="XI">XI.--The <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> had by this time led their forces over through the
narrow defile and the territories of the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, and had arrived at the
territories of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, and were ravaging their lands. The <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, as
they could not defend themselves and their possessions against them,
send ambassadors to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> to ask assistance, [pleading] that they had
at all times so well deserved of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, that their fields
ought not to have been laid waste--their children carried off into
slavery--their towns stormed, almost within sight of our army. At the
same time the <tribe name="Ambarri">Ambarri</tribe>, the friends and kinsmen of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, apprise
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> that it was not easy for them, now that their fields had been
devastated, to ward off the violence of the enemy from their towns: the
<tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe> likewise, who had villages and possessions on the other side
of the <place river="rhone">Rhone</place>, betake themselves in flight to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> and assure him that
they had nothing remaining, except the soil of their land. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>,
induced by these circumstances, decides that he ought not to wait until
the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, after destroying all the property of his allies, should
arrive among the Santones.</chapter>

<chapter n="XII">XII.--There is a river [called] the <place river="saone">Saone</place>, which flows through the
territories of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> and <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> into the <place river="rhone">Rhone</place> with such incredible
slowness, that it cannot be determined by the eye in which direction it
flows. This the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> were crossing by rafts and boats joined
together. When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> was informed by spies that the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> had
already conveyed three parts of their forces across that river, but that
the fourth part was left behind on this side of the <place river="saone">Saone</place>, he set out
from the camp with three legions during the third watch, and came up
with that division which had not yet crossed the river. Attacking them,
encumbered with baggage, and not expecting him, he cut to pieces a great
part of them; the rest betook themselves to flight, and concealed
themselves in the nearest woods. That canton [which was cut down] was
called the Tigurine; for the whole Helvetian state is divided into four
cantons. This single canton having left their country, within the
recollection of our fathers, had slain <persName eth="roman" role="consul">Lucius Cassius</persName> the consul, and
had made his army pass under the yoke [B.C. 107]. Thus, whether by
chance, or by the design of the immortal gods, that part of the
Helvetian state which had brought a signal calamity upon the Roman
people was the first to pay the penalty. In this <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> avenged not only
the public, but also his own personal wrongs, because the <tribe name="Tigurini">Tigurini</tribe> had
slain <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Lucius Piso</persName> the lieutenant [of Cassius], the grandfather of Lucius
Calpurnius Piso, his [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s] father-in-law, in the same battle as
Cassius himself.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIII">XIII.--This battle ended, that he might be able to come up with the
remaining forces of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, he procures a bridge to be made across
the <place river="saone">Saone</place>, and thus leads his army over. The <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, confused by his
sudden arrival, when they found that he had effected in one day what
they themselves had with the utmost difficulty accomplished in twenty,
namely, the crossing of the river, send ambassadors to him; at the head
of which embassy was <persName eth="helvetii" role="commander">Divico</persName>, who had been commander of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> in
the war against Cassius. He thus treats with <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>:--that, "if the
<tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> would make peace with the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> they would go to that
part and there remain, where <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> might appoint and desire them to be;
but if he should persist in persecuting them with war, that he ought to
remember both the ancient disgrace of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> and the
characteristic valour of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>. As to his having attacked one
canton by surprise, [at a time] when those who had crossed the river
could not bring assistance to their friends, that he ought not on that
account to ascribe very much to his own valour, or despise them; that
they had so learned from their sires and ancestors, as to rely more on
valour than on artifice or stratagem. Wherefore let him not bring it to
pass that the place, where they were standing, should acquire a name,
from the disaster of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> and the destruction of their army
or transmit the remembrance [of such an event to posterity]."</chapter>

<chapter n="XIV">XIV.--To these words <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> thus replied:--that "on that very account he
felt less hesitation, because he kept in remembrance those circumstances
which the Helvetian ambassadors had mentioned, and that he felt the more
indignant at them, in proportion as they had happened undeservedly to
the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>: for if they had been conscious of having done any
wrong it would not have been difficult to be on their guard, but for
that very reason had they been deceived, because neither were they aware
that any offence had been given by them, on account of which they should
be afraid, nor did they think that they ought to be afraid without
cause. But even if he were willing to forget their former outrage, could
he also lay aside the remembrance of the late wrongs, in that they had
against his will attempted a route through the Province by force, in
that they had molested the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, the <tribe name="Ambarri">Ambarri</tribe>, and the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>? That
as to their so insolently boasting of their victory, and as to their
being astonished that they had so long committed their outrages with
impunity, [both these things] tended to the same point; for the immortal
gods are wont to allow those persons whom they wish to punish for their
guilt sometimes a greater prosperity and longer impunity, in order that
they may suffer the more severely from a reverse of circumstances.
Although these things are so, yet, if hostages were to be given him by
them in order that he may be assured they will do what they promise, and
provided they will give satisfaction to the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> for the outrages which
they had committed against them and their allies, and likewise to the
<tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>, he [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] will make peace with them." <persName eth="helvetii" role="commander">Divico</persName> replied, that
"the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> had been so trained by their ancestors that they were
accustomed to receive, not to give, hostages; of that fact the Roman
people were witness." Having given this reply, he withdrew.</chapter>

<chapter n="XV">XV.--On the following day they move their camp from that place; <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>
does the same, and sends forward all his cavalry, to the number of four
thousand (which he had drawn together from all parts of the Province and
from the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> and their allies), to observe towards what parts the
enemy are directing their march. These, having too eagerly pursued the
enemy's rear, come to a battle with the cavalry of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> in a
disadvantageous place, and a few of our men fall. The <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, elated
with this battle because they had with five hundred horse repulsed so
large a body of horse, began to face us more boldly, sometimes too from
their rear to provoke our men by an attack. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> [however] restrained
his men from battle, deeming it sufficient for the present to prevent
the enemy from rapine, forage, and depredation. They marched for about
fifteen days in such a manner that there was not more than five or six
miles between the enemy's rear and our van.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVI">XVI.--Meanwhile, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> kept daily importuning the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> for the corn
which they had promised in the name of their state; for, in consequence
of the coldness (<place region="gaul">Gaul</place> being, as before said, situated towards the
north), not only was the corn in the fields not ripe, but there was not
in store a sufficiently large quantity even of fodder: besides he was
unable to use the corn which he had conveyed in ships up the river
<place river="saone">Saone</place>, because the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, from whom he was unwilling to retire, had
diverted their march from the <place river="saone">Saone</place>. The <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> kept deferring from day
to day, and saying that it was being "collected--brought in--on the
road." When he saw that he was put off too long, and that the day was
close at hand on which he ought to serve out the corn to his soldiers,--
having called together their chiefs, of whom he had a great number in
his camp, among them <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>, and Liscus who was invested with the
chief magistracy (whom the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> style the Vergobretus, and who is
elected annually, and has power of life and death over his countrymen),
he severely reprimands them, because he is not assisted by them on so
urgent an occasion, when the enemy were so close at hand, and when
[corn] could neither be bought nor taken from the fields, particularly
as, in a great measure urged by their prayers, he had undertaken the
war; much more bitterly, therefore, does he complain of his being
forsaken.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVII">XVII.--Then at length Liscus, moved by <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s speech, discloses what
he had hitherto kept secret:--that "there are some whose influence with
the people is very great, who, though private men, have more power than
the magistrates themselves: that these by seditious and violent language
are deterring the populace from contributing the corn which they ought
to supply; [by telling them] that, if they cannot any longer retain the
supremacy of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, it were better to submit to the government of <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>
than of Romans, nor ought they to doubt that, if the Romans should
overpower the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, they would wrest their freedom from the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>
together with the remainder of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>. By these very men [said he] are our
plans, and whatever is done in the camp, disclosed to the enemy; that
they could not be restrained by _him_: nay more, he was well aware that,
though compelled by necessity, he had disclosed the matter to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, at
how great a risk he had done it; and for that reason, he had been silent
as long as he could."</chapter>

<chapter n="XVIII">XVIII.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> perceived that, by this speech of Liscus, <persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName>, the
brother of <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>, was indicated; but, as he was unwilling that
these matters should be discussed while so many were present, he
speedily dismisses the council, but detains Liscus: he inquires from him
when alone, about those things which he had said in the meeting. He
[Liscus] speaks more unreservedly and boldly. He [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] makes
inquiries on the same points privately of others, and discovers that it
is all true; that "<persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName> is the person, a man of the highest daring,
in great favour with the people on account of his liberality, a man
eager for a revolution: that for a great many years he has been in the
habit of contracting for the customs and all the other taxes of the
<tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> at a small cost, because when _he_ bids, no one dares to bid
against him. By these means he has both increased his own private
property and amassed great means for giving largesses; that he maintains
constantly at his own expense and keeps about his own person a great
number of cavalry, and that not only at home, but even among the
neighbouring states, he has great influence, and for the sake of
strengthening this influence has given his mother in marriage among the
Bituriges to a man the most noble and most influential there; that he
has himself taken a wife from among the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, and has given his
sister by the mother's side and his female relations in marriage into
other states; that he favours and wishes well to the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> on account
of this connection; and that he hates <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> and the Romans, on his own
account, because by their arrival his power was weakened, and his
brother, <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>, restored to his former position of influence and
dignity: that, if anything should happen to the Romans, he entertains
the highest hope of gaining the sovereignty by means of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>,
but that under the government of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> he despairs not only
of royalty but even of that influence which he already has." <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>
discovered too, on inquiring into the unsuccessful cavalry engagement
which had taken place a few days before, that the commencement of that
flight had been made by <persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName> and his cavalry (for <persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName> was in
command of the cavalry which the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> had sent for aid to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>); that
by their flight the rest of the cavalry was dismayed.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIX">XIX.--After learning these circumstances, since to these suspicions the
most unequivocal facts were added, viz., that he had led the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>
through the territories of the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>; that he had provided that
hostages should be mutually given; that he had done all these things,
not only without any orders of his [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s] and of his own state's,
but even without their [the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>] knowing anything of it themselves;
that he [<persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName>] was reprimanded by the [chief] magistrate of the
<tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>; he [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] considered that there was sufficient reason why he
should either punish him himself, or order the state to do so. One thing
[however] stood in the way of all this--that he had learned by
experience his brother <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>'s very high regard for the Roman
people, his great affection towards him, his distinguished faithfulness,
justice, and moderation; for he was afraid lest by the punishment of
this man, he should hurt the feelings of <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>. Therefore, before
he attempted anything, he orders <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName> to be summoned to him, and
when the ordinary interpreters had been withdrawn, converses with him
through Caius Valerius Procillus, chief of the province of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, an
intimate friend of his, in whom he reposed the highest confidence in
everything; at the same time he reminds him of what was said about
<persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName> in the council of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, when he himself was present, and
shows what each had said of him privately in his [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s] own
presence; he begs and exhorts him, that, without offence to his
feelings, he may either himself pass judgment on him [<persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName>] after
trying the case, or else order the [Aeduan] state to do so.

XX.-<persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>, embracing <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, begins to implore him, with many
tears, that "he would not pass any very severe sentence upon his
brother; saying, that he knows that those [charges] are true, and that
nobody suffered more pain on that account than he himself did; for when
he himself could effect a very great deal by his influence at home and
in the rest of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and he [<persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName>] very little on account of his
youth, the latter had become powerful through his means, which power and
strength he used not only to the lessening of his [<persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>]
popularity, but almost to his ruin; that he, however, was influenced
both by fraternal affection and by public opinion. But if anything very
severe from <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> should befall him [<persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName>], no one would think that
it had been done without his consent, since he himself held such a place
in <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s friendship; from which circumstance it would arise that the
affections of the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> would be estranged from him." As he was
with tears begging these things of <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> in many words, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> takes
his right hand, and, comforting him, begs him to make an end of
entreating, and assures him that his regard for him is so great that he
forgives both the injuries of the republic and his private wrongs, at
his desire and prayers. He summons <persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName> to him; he brings in his
brother; he points out what he censures in him; he lays before him what
he of himself perceives, and what the state complains of; he warns him
for the future to avoid all grounds of suspicion; he says that he
pardons the past, for the sake of his brother, <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>. He sets spies
over <persName eth="aedui" role="chieftain">Dumnorix</persName> that he may be able to know what he does, and with whom he
communicates.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXI">XXI.--Being on the same day informed by his scouts that the enemy had
encamped at the foot of a mountain eight miles from his own camp, he
sent persons to ascertain what the nature of the mountain was, and of
what kind the ascent on every side. Word was brought back that it was
easy. During the third watch he orders <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName>, his lieutenant
with praetorian powers, to ascend to the highest ridge of the mountain
with two legions, and with those as guides who had examined the road; he
explains what his plan is. He himself during the fourth watch, hastens
to them by the same route by which the enemy had gone, and sends on all
the cavalry before him. Publius <persName eth="roman">Considius</persName>, who was reputed to be very
experienced in military affairs, and had been in the army of Lucius
Sulla, and afterwards in that of Marcus Crassus, is sent forward with
the scouts.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXII">XXII.--At day-break, when the summit of the mountain was in the
possession of <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName>, and he himself was not further off than a
mile and half from the enemy's camp, nor, as he afterwards ascertained
from the captives, had either his arrival or that of <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName> been
discovered; <persName eth="roman">Considius</persName>, with his horse at full gallop, comes up to him--
says that the mountain which he [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] wished should be seized by
<persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName>, is in possession of the enemy; that he has discovered this by
the Gallic arms and ensigns. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> leads off his forces to the next
hill: [and] draws them up in battle-order. <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName>, as he had been
ordered by <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> not to come to an engagement unless [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s] own
forces were seen near the enemy's camp, that the attack upon the enemy
might be made on every side at the same time, was, after having taken
possession of the mountain, waiting for our men, and refraining from
battle. When, at length, the day was far advanced, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> learned
through spies that the mountain was in possession of his own men, and
that the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> had moved their camp, and that <persName eth="roman">Considius</persName>, struck with
fear, had reported to him, as seen, that which he had not seen. On that
day he follows the enemy at his usual distance, and pitches his camp
three miles from theirs.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIII">XXIII.--The next day (as there remained in all only two days' space [to
the time] when he must serve out the corn to his army, and as he was not
more than eighteen miles from Bibracte, by far the largest and best-stored
town of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>) he thought that he ought to provide for a
supply of corn; and diverted his march from the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, and advanced
rapidly to Bibracte. This circumstance is reported to the enemy by some
deserters from Lucius Aemilius, a captain of the Gallic horse. The
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, either because they thought that the Romans, struck with
terror, were retreating from them, the more so, as the day before,
though they had seized on the higher grounds, they had not joined
battle; or because they flattered themselves that they might be cut off
from the provisions, altering their plan and changing their route, began
to pursue and to annoy our men in the rear.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIV">XXIV.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, when he observes this, draws off his forces to the next
hill, and sent the cavalry to sustain the attack of the enemy. He
himself, meanwhile, drew up on the middle of the hill a triple line of
his four veteran legions in such a manner that he placed above him on
the very summit the two legions which he had lately levied in Hither
<place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and all the auxiliaries; and he ordered that the whole mountain
should be covered with men, and that meanwhile the baggage should be
brought together into one place, and the position be protected by those
who were posted in the upper line. The <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, having followed with
all their waggons, collected their baggage into one place: they
themselves, after having repulsed our cavalry and formed a phalanx,
advanced up to our front line in very close order.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXV">XXV.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, having removed out of sight first his own horse, then
those of all, that he might make the danger of all equal, and do away
with the hope of flight, after encouraging his men, joined battle. His
soldiers, hurling their javelins from the higher ground, easily broke
the enemy's phalanx. That being dispersed, they made a charge on them
with drawn swords. It was a great hindrance to the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> in fighting,
that, when several of their bucklers had been by one stroke of the
(Roman) javelins pierced through and pinned fast together, as the point
of the iron had bent itself, they could neither pluck it out, nor, with
their left hand entangled, fight with sufficient ease; so that many,
after having long tossed their arm about, chose rather to cast away the
buckler from their hand, and to fight with their person unprotected. At
length, worn out with wounds, they began to give way, and as there was
in the neighbourhood a mountain about a mile off, to betake themselves
thither. When the mountain had been gained, and our men were advancing
up, the <tribe name="boii">Boii</tribe> and <tribe name="tulingi">Tulingi</tribe>, who with about <event type="battle" victor="romans" figure="15000">15,000</event> men closed the enemy's
line of march and served as a guard to their rear, having assailed our
men on the exposed flank as they advanced [prepared] to surround them;
upon seeing which, the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, who had betaken themselves to the
mountain, began to press on again and renew the battle. The Romans
having faced about, advanced to the attack in two divisions; the first
and second line to withstand those who had been defeated and driven off
the field; the third to receive those who were just arriving.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVI">XXVI.--Thus was the contest long and vigorously carried on with doubtful
success. When they could no longer withstand the attacks of our men, the
one division, as they had begun to do, betook themselves to the
mountain; the other repaired to their baggage and waggons. For during
the whole of this battle, although the fight lasted from the seventh
hour [_i.e._ 12 (noon)--1 P.M.] to eventide, no one could see an enemy
with his back turned. The fight was carried on also at the baggage till
late in the night, for they had set waggons in the way as a rampart, and
from the higher ground kept throwing weapons upon our men, as they came
on, and some from between the waggons and the wheels kept darting their
lances and javelins from beneath, and wounding our men. After the fight
had lasted some time, our men gained possession of their baggage and
camp. There the daughter and one of the sons of <persName eth="helvetii" role="arist">Orgetorix</persName> were taken.
After that battle about 130,000 men [of the enemy] remained alive, who
marched incessantly during the whole of that night; and after a march
discontinued for no part of the night, arrived in the territories of the
<tribe name="Lingones">Lingones</tribe> on the fourth day, whilst our men, having stopped for three
days, both on account of the wounds of the soldiers and the burial of
the slain, had not been able to follow them. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> sent letters and
messengers to the <tribe name="Lingones">Lingones</tribe> [with orders] that they should not assist
them with corn or with anything else; for that if they should assist
them, he would regard them in the same light as the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>. After the
three days' interval he began to follow them himself with all his
forces.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVII">XXVII.--The <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, compelled by the want of everything, sent
ambassadors to him about a surrender. When these had met him in the way
and had thrown themselves at his feet, and speaking in suppliant tone
had with tears sued for peace, and [when] he had ordered them to await
his arrival, in the place where they then were, they obeyed his
commands. When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> arrived at that place, he demanded hostages, their
arms, and the slaves who had deserted to them. Whilst those things are
being sought for and got together, after a night's interval, about 6000
men of that canton which is called the Verbigene, whether terrified by
fear, lest, after delivering up their arms, they should suffer
punishment, or else induced by the hope of safety, because they supposed
that, amid so vast a multitude of those who had surrendered themselves,
_their_ flight might either be concealed or entirely overlooked, having
at night-fall departed out of the camp of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, hastened to the
<place river="rhine">Rhine</place> and the territories of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVIII">XXVIII.--But when <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> discovered this, he commanded those through
whose territories they had gone, to seek them, out and to bring them
back again, if they meant to be acquitted before him; and considered
them, when brought back, in the light of enemies; he admitted all the
rest to a surrender, upon their delivering up the hostages, arms, and
deserters. He ordered the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, the <tribe name="tulingi">Tulingi</tribe>, and the <tribe name="latobrigi">Latobrigi</tribe> to
return to their territories from which they had come, and as there was
at home nothing whereby they might support their hunger, all the
productions of the earth having been destroyed, he commanded the
<tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe> to let them have a plentiful supply of corn; and ordered them
to rebuild the towns and villages which they had burnt. This he did,
chiefly on this account, because he was unwilling that the country, from
which the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> had departed, should be untenanted, lest the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>,
who dwell on the other side of the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, should, on account of the
excellence of the lands, cross over from their own territories into
those of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, and become borderers upon the province of Gaul
and the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>. He granted the petition of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, that they
might settle the <tribe name="boii">Boii</tribe>, in their own (_i.e._ in the Aeduan) territories,
as these were known to be of distinguished valour to whom they gave
lands, and whom they afterwards admitted to the same state of rights and
freedom as themselves.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIX">XXIX.--In the camp of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, lists were found, drawn up in Greek
characters, and were brought to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, in which an estimate had been
drawn up, name by name, of the number which had gone forth from their
country of those who were able to bear arms; and likewise the boys, the
old men, and the women, separately. Of all which items the total was:-

Of the _<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>_ [lit. of the heads of the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>] 263,000
Of the _<tribe name="Tulingi">Tulingi</tribe>_                                       36,000
Of the _<tribe name="latobrigi">Latobrigi</tribe>_                                     14,000
Of the _<tribe name="rauraci">Rauraci</tribe>_                                       23,000
Of the _<tribe name="boii">Boii</tribe>_                                          32,000
                                                      -------
The sum of all amounted to                            368,000

Out of these, such as could bear arms [amounted] to about 92,000. When
the _census_ of those who returned home was taken, as <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had
commanded, the number was found to be 110,000.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXX">XXX.--When the war with the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> was concluded, ambassadors from
almost all parts of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, the chiefs of states, assembled to
congratulate <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, [saying] that they were well aware, that, although
he had taken vengeance on the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> in war, for the old wrongs done
by them to the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, yet that circumstance had happened no less
to the benefit of the land of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> than of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, because the
<tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, while their affairs were most flourishing, had quitted their
country with the design of making war upon the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and
seizing the government of it, and selecting, out of a great abundance,
that spot for an abode which they should judge to be the most convenient
and most productive of all <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and hold the rest of the states as
tributaries. They requested that they might be allowed to proclaim an
assembly of the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> for a particular day, and to do that with
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s permission, [stating] that they had some things which, with the
general consent, they wished to ask of him. This request having been
granted, they appointed a day for the assembly, and ordained by an oath
with each other, that no one should disclose [their deliberations]
except those to whom this [office] should be assigned by the general
assembly.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXI">XXXI.--When that assembly was dismissed, the same chiefs of states, who
had before been to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, returned, and asked that they might be
allowed to treat with him privately (in secret) concerning the safety of
themselves and of all. That request having been obtained, they all threw
themselves in tears at <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s feet, [saying] that they no less begged
and earnestly desired that what they might say should not be disclosed
than that they might obtain those things which they wished for; inasmuch
as they saw that, if a disclosure were made, they should be put to the
greatest tortures. For these <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName> the Aeduan spoke and told him:--
"That there were two parties in the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>: that the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> stood
at the head of one of these, the Arverni of the other. After these had
been violently struggling with one another for the superiority for many
years, it came to pass that the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> were called in for hire by the
Arverni and the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>. That about 15,000 of them [_i.e._ of the
<tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>] had at first crossed the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>: but after that these wild and
savage men had become enamoured of the lands and the refinement and the
abundance of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, more were brought over, that there were now as
many as 120,000 of them in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>: that with these the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> and their
dependants had repeatedly struggled in arms, that they had been routed
and had sustained a great calamity--had lost all their nobility, all
their senate, all their cavalry. And that broken by such engagements and
calamities, although they had formerly been very powerful in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, both
from their own valour and from the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>'s hospitality and
friendship, they were now compelled to give the chief nobles of their
state as hostages to the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, and to bind their state by an oath,
that they would neither demand hostages in return, nor supplicate aid
from the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, nor refuse to be for ever under their sway and
empire. That he was the only one out of all the state of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> who
could not be prevailed upon to take the oath or to give his children as
hostages. On that account he had fled from his state and had gone to the
senate at Rome to beseech aid, as he alone was bound neither by oath nor
hostages. But a worse thing had befallen the victorious <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> than the
vanquished <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, for Ariovistus, the king of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, had settled
in their territories, and had seized upon a third of their land, which
was the best in the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and was now ordering them to depart
from another third part, because a few months previously 24,000 men of
the Harudes had come to him, for whom room and settlements must be
provided. The consequence would be, that in a few years they would all
be driven from the territories of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and all the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> would cross
the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>; for neither must the land of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> be compared with the land
of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, nor must the habit of living of the latter be put on a
level with that of the former. Moreover, [as for] Ariovistus, no sooner
did he defeat the forces of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> in a battle, which took place at
Magetobria, than [he began] to lord it haughtily and cruelly, to demand
as hostages the children of all the principal nobles, and wreak on them
every kind of cruelty, if everything was not done at his nod or
pleasure; that he was a savage, passionate, and reckless man, and that
his commands could no longer be borne. Unless there was some aid in
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> and the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> must all do the same thing that
the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe> had done, [viz.] emigrate from their country, and seek
another dwelling place, other settlements remote from the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, and
try whatever fortune may fall to their lot. If these things were to be
disclosed to Ariovistus, [<persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName> adds] that he doubts not that he
would inflict the most severe punishment on all the hostages who are in
his possession, [and says] that <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> could, either by his own
influence and by that of his army, or by his late victory, or by name of
the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, intimidate him, so as to prevent a greater number of
<tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> being brought over the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, and could protect all <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> from
the outrages of Ariovistus."</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXII">XXXII.--When this speech had been delivered by <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>, all who were
present began with loud lamentation to entreat assistance of <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>.
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> noticed that the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> were the only people of all who did none
of those things which the others did, but, with their heads bowed down,
gazed on the earth in sadness. Wondering what was the reason of this
conduct, he inquired of themselves. No reply did the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> make, but
silently continued in the same sadness. When he had repeatedly
inquired of them and could not elicit any answer at all, the same
<persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName> the Aeduan answered, that--"the lot of the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> was more
wretched and grievous than that of the rest, on this account, because
they alone durst not even in secret complain or supplicate aid; and
shuddered at the cruelty of Ariovistus [even when] absent, just as if he
were present; for, to the rest, despite of everything, there was an
opportunity of flight given; but all tortures must be endured by the
<tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, who had admitted Ariovistus within their territories, and whose
towns were all in his power."</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXIII">XXXIII.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, on being informed of these things, cheered the minds of
the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> with his words, and promised that this affair should be an
object of his concern, [saying] that he had great hopes that Ariovistus,
induced both by his kindness and his power, would put an end to his
oppression. After delivering this speech, he dismissed the assembly;
and, besides those statements, many circumstances induced him to think
that this affair ought to be considered and taken up by him; especially
as he saw that the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, styled [as they had been] repeatedly by the
senate "brethren" and "kinsmen," were held in the thraldom and dominion
of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, and understood that their hostages were with Ariovistus
and the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, which in so mighty an empire [as that] of the Roman
people he considered very disgraceful to himself and the republic. That,
moreover, the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> should by degrees become accustomed to cross the
<place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, and that a great body of them should come into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, he saw
[would be] dangerous to the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, and judged that wild and
savage men would not be likely to restrain themselves, after they had
possessed themselves of all <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, from going forth into the province and
thence marching into <place region="italy">Italy</place> (as the Cimbri and Teutones had done before
them), particularly as the <place river="rhone">Rhone</place> [was the sole barrier that] separated
the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> from our province. Against which events he thought he ought
to provide as speedily as possible. Moreover, Ariovistus, for his part,
had assumed to himself such pride and arrogance that he was felt to be
quite insufferable.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXIV">XXXIV.--He therefore determined to send ambassadors to Ariovistus to
demand of him to name some intermediate spot for a conference between
the two, [saying] that he wished to treat with him on state-business and
matters of the highest importance to both of them. To this embassy
Ariovistus replied, that if he himself had had need of anything from
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, he would have gone to him; and that if <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> wanted anything
from him he ought to come to him. That, besides, neither dare he go
without an army into those parts of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> which <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had possession of,
nor could he, without great expense and trouble, draw his army together
to one place; that to him, moreover, it appeared strange what business
either <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> or the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> at all had in his own <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, which he
had conquered in war.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXV">XXXV.--When these answers were reported to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, he sends ambassadors
to him a second time with this message "Since, after having been treated
with so much kindness by himself and the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> (as he had in his
consulship [B.C. 59] been styled 'king and friend' by the senate), he
makes this recompense to [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] himself and the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, [viz.]
that when invited to a conference he demurs, and does not think that it
concerns him to advise and inform himself about an object of mutual
interest, these are the things which he requires of him; first, that he
do not any more bring over any body of men across the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place> into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>;
in the next place, that he restore the hostages which he has from the
<tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, and grant the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> permission to restore to them with his
consent those hostages which they have, and that he neither provoke the
<tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> by outrage nor make war upon them or their allies; if he would
accordingly do this," [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> says] that "he himself and the Roman
people will entertain a perpetual feeling of favour and friendship
towards him; but that if he [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] does not obtain [his desires], that
he (forasmuch as in the consulship of <persName eth="roman" role="consul">Marcus Messala</persName> and <persName eth="roman" role="consul">Marcus Piso</persName>
[B.C. 61] the senate had decreed that, whoever should have the
administration of the province of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> should, as far as he could do so
consistently with the interests of the republic, protect the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> and
the other friends of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>) will not overlook the wrongs of
the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>."</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXVI">XXXVI.--To this Ariovistus replied, that "the right of war was, that
they who had conquered should govern those whom they had conquered, in
what manner they pleased; that in that way the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> were wont to
govern the nations which they had conquered, not according to the
dictation of any other, but according to their own discretion. If he for
his part did not dictate to the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> as to the manner in which
they were to exercise their right, he ought not to be obstructed by the
<tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> in his right; that the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, inasmuch as they had tried
the fortune of war and had engaged in arms and been conquered, had
become tributaries to him; that <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> was doing a great injustice, in
that by his arrival he was making his revenues less valuable to him;
that he should not restore their hostages to the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, but should not
make war wrongfully either upon them or their allies, if they abided by
that which had been agreed on, and paid their tribute annually: if they
did _not_ continue to do that, the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>'s name of 'brothers'
would avail them nought. As to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s threatening him that be would
not overlook the wrongs of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, [he said] that no one had ever
entered into a contest with _him_ [Ariovistus] without utter ruin to
himself. That <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> might enter the lists when he chose; he would feel
what the invincible <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, well-trained [as they were] beyond all
others to arms, who for fourteen years had not been beneath a roof,
could achieve by their valour."</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXVII">XXXVII.--At the same time that this message was delivered to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>,
ambassadors came from the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> and the Treviri; from the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> to
complain that the Harudes, who had lately been brought over into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>,
were ravaging their territories; that they had not been able to purchase
peace from Ariovistus, even by giving hostages: and from the Treviri,
[to state] that a hundred cantons of the Suevi had encamped on the banks
of the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, and were attempting to cross it; that the brothers, Nasuas
and Cimberius, headed them. Being greatly alarmed at these things,
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> thought that he ought to use all despatch, lest, if this new band
of Suevi should unite with the old troops of Ariovistus, he [Ariovistus]
might be less easily withstood. Having, therefore, as quickly as he
could, provided a supply of corn, he hastened to Ariovistus by forced
marches.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXVIII">XXXVIII.--When he had proceeded three days' journey, word was brought to
him that Ariovistus was hastening with all his forces to seize on
Vesontio, which is the largest town of the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, and had advanced
three days' journey from his territories. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> thought that he ought
to take the greatest precautions lest this should happen, for there was
in that town a most ample supply of everything which was serviceable for
war; and so fortified was it by the nature of the ground as to afford a
great facility for protracting the war, inasmuch as the river Doubs
almost surrounds the whole town, as though it were traced round it with
a pair of compasses. A mountain of great height shuts in the remaining
space, which is not more than 600 feet, where the river leaves a gap, in
such a manner that the roots of that mountain extend to the river's bank
on either side. A wall thrown around it makes a citadel of this
[mountain], and connects it with the town. Hither <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> hastens by
forced marches by night and day, and, after having seized the town,
stations a garrison there.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXIX">XXXIX.--Whilst he is tarrying a few days at Vesontio, on account of corn
and provisions; from the inquiries of our men and the reports of the
<tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> and traders (who asserted that the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> were men of huge
stature, of incredible valour and practice in arms, that ofttimes they,
on encountering them, could not bear even their countenance, and the
fierceness of their eyes)--so great a panic on a sudden seized the whole
army, as to discompose the minds and spirits of all in no slight degree.
This first arose from the tribunes of the soldiers, the prefects and the
rest, who, having followed <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> from the city [Rome] from motives of
friendship, had no great experience in military affairs. And alleging,
some of them one reason, some another, which they said made it necessary
for them to depart, they requested that by his consent they might be
allowed to withdraw; some, influenced by shame, stayed behind in order
that they might avoid the suspicion of cowardice. These could neither
compose their countenance, nor even sometimes check their tears: but
hidden in their tents, either bewailed their fate, or deplored with
their comrades the general danger. Wills were sealed universally
throughout the whole camp. By the expressions and cowardice of these
men, even those who possessed great experience in the camp, both
soldiers and centurions, and those [the decurions] who were in command
of the cavalry, were gradually disconcerted. Such of them as wished to
be considered less alarmed, said that they did not dread the enemy, but
feared the narrowness of the roads and the vastness of the forests which
lay between them and Ariovistus, or else that the supplies could not be
brought up readily enough. Some even declared to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> that when he
gave orders for the camp to be moved and the troops to advance, the
soldiers would not be obedient to the command, nor advance in
consequence of their fear.</chapter>

<chapter n="XL">XL.--When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> observed these things, having called a council, and
summoned to it the centurions of all the companies, he severely
reprimanded them, "particularly for supposing that it belonged to them
to inquire or conjecture, either in what direction they were marching,
or with what object. That Ariovistus, during his [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s] consulship,
had most anxiously sought after the friendship of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>; why
should any one judge that he would so rashly depart from his duty? He
for his part was persuaded that, when his demands were known and the
fairness of the terms considered, he would reject neither his nor the
<tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>'s favour. But even if, driven on by rage and madness, he
should make war upon them, what after all were they afraid of?--or why
should they despair either of their own valour or of his zeal? Of that
enemy a trial had been made within our fathers' recollection, when, on
the defeat of the Cimbri and Teutones by Caius Marius, the army was
regarded as having deserved no less praise than their commander himself.
It had been made lately, too, in <place region="italy">Italy</place>; during the rebellion of the
slaves, whom, however, the experience and training which they had
received from us, assisted in some respect. From which a judgment might
be formed of the advantages which resolution carries with it,--inasmuch
as those whom for some time they had groundlessly dreaded when unarmed,
they had afterwards vanquished, when well armed and flushed with
success. In short, that these were the same men whom the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, in
frequent encounters, not only in their own territories, but also in
theirs [the German], have generally vanquished, and yet cannot have been
a match for our army. If the unsuccessful battle and flight of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>
disquieted any, these, if they made inquiries, might discover that, when
the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> had been tired out by the long duration of the war,
Ariovistus, after he had many months kept himself in his camp and in the
marshes, and had given no opportunity for an engagement, fell suddenly
upon them, by this time despairing of a battle and scattered in all
directions, and was victorious more through stratagem and cunning than
valour. But though there had been room for such stratagem against savage
and unskilled men, not even [Ariovistus] himself expected that thereby
our armies could be entrapped. That those who ascribed their fear to a
pretence about the [deficiency of] supplies and the narrowness of the
roads, acted presumptuously, as they seemed either to distrust their
general's discharge of his duty, or to dictate to him. That these things
were his concern; that the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, the Leuci, and the <tribe name="Lingones">Lingones</tribe> were to
furnish the corn; and that it was already ripe in the fields; that as to
the road they would soon be able to judge for themselves. As to its
being reported that the soldiers would not be obedient to command, or
advance, he was not at all disturbed at that; for he knew that in the
case of all those whose army had not been obedient to command, either
upon some mismanagement of an affair, fortune had deserted them, or,
that upon some crime being discovered, covetousness had been clearly
proved [against them]. His integrity had been seen throughout his whole
life, his good fortune in the war with the <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>. That he would
therefore instantly set about what he had intended to put off till a
more distant day, and would break up his camp the next night, in the
fourth watch, that he might ascertain, as soon as possible, whether a
sense of honour and duty, or whether fear had more influence with them.
But that, if no one else should follow, yet he would go with only the
tenth legion, of which he had no misgivings, and it should be his
praetorian cohort."--This legion <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had both greatly favoured, and
in it, on account of its valour, placed the greatest confidence.

XLI.-Upon the delivery of this speech, the minds of all were changed in
a surprising, manner, and the highest ardour and eagerness for
prosecuting the war were engendered; and the tenth legion was the first
to return thanks to him, through their military tribunes, for his having
expressed this most favourable opinion of them; and assured him that
they were quite ready to prosecute the war. Then, the other legions
endeavoured, through their military tribunes and the centurions of the
principal companies, to excuse themselves to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, [saying] that they
had never either doubted or feared, or supposed that the determination
of the conduct of the war was theirs and not their general's. Having
accepted their excuse, and having had the road carefully reconnoitred by
<persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>, because in him of all others he had the greatest faith, [he
found] that by a circuitous route of more than fifty miles he might lead
his army through open parts; he then set out in the fourth watch, as he
had said [he would]. On the seventh day, as he did not discontinue his
march, he was informed by scouts that the forces of Ariovistus were only
four and twenty miles distant from ours.</chapter>

<chapter n="XLII">XLII.--Upon being apprised of <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s arrival, Ariovistus sends
ambassadors to him, [saying] that what he had before requested as to a
conference, might now, as far as his permission went, take place, since
he [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] had approached nearer, and he considered that he might now
do it without danger. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> did not reject the proposal and began to
think that he was now returning to a rational state of mind, as he
spontaneously proffered that which he had previously refused to him when
requesting it; and was in great hopes that, in consideration of his own
and the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>'s great favours towards him, the issue would be
that he would desist from his obstinacy upon his demands being made
known. The fifth day after that was appointed as the day of conference.
Meanwhile, as ambassadors were being often sent to and fro between them,
Ariovistus demanded that <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> should not bring any foot-soldier with
him to the conference, [saying] that "he was afraid of being ensnared by
him through treachery; that both should come accompanied by cavalry;
that he would not come on any other condition." <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, as he neither
wished that the conference should, by an excuse thrown in the way, be
set aside, nor durst trust his life to the cavalry of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, decided
that it would be most expedient to take away from the Gallic cavalry all
their horses, and thereon to mount the legionary soldiers of the tenth
legion, in which he placed the greatest confidence; in order that he
might have a body-guard as trustworthy as possible, should there be any
need for action. And when this was done, one of the soldiers of the
tenth legion said, not without a touch of humour, "that <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> did more
for them than he had promised; he had promised to have the tenth legion
in place of his praetorian cohort; but he now converted them into
horse."</chapter>

<chapter n="XLIII">XLIII.--There was a large plain, and in it a mound of earth of
considerable size. This spot was at nearly an equal distance from both
camps. Thither, as had been appointed, they came for the conference.
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> stationed the legion, which he had brought [with him] on
horseback, 200 paces from this mound. The cavalry of Ariovistus also
took their stand at an equal distance. Ariovistus then demanded that
they should confer on horseback, and that, besides themselves, they
should bring with them ten men each to the conference. When they were
come to the place, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, in the opening of his speech, detailed his
own and the senate's favours towards him [Ariovistus], "in that he had
been styled king, in that [he had been styled] friend, by the senate--
in that very considerable presents had been sent him; which circumstance
he informed him had both fallen to the lot of few, and had usually been
bestowed in consideration of important personal services; that he,
although he had neither an introduction, nor a just ground for the
request, had obtained these honours through the kindness and munificence
of himself [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] and the senate. He informed him too, how old and how
just were the grounds of connexion that existed between themselves [the
Romans] and the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, what decrees of the senate had been passed in
their favour, and how frequent and how honourable; how from time
immemorial the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> had held the supremacy of the whole of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>; even
[said <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] before they had sought our friendship; that it was the
custom of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> to desire not only that its allies and
friends should lose none of their property, but be advanced in
influence, dignity, and honour: who then could endure that what they had
brought with them to the friendship of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, should be torn
from them?" He then made the same demands which he had commissioned the
ambassadors to make, that [Ariovistus] should not make war either upon
the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> or their allies, that he should restore the hostages; that, if
he could not send back to their country any part of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, he
should at all events suffer none of them any more to cross the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>.</chapter>

<chapter n="XLIV">XLIV.--Ariovistus replied briefly to the demands of <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>; but
expatiated largely on his own virtues, "that he had crossed the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>
not of his own accord, but on being invited and sent for by the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>;
that he had not left home and kindred without great expectations and
great rewards; that he had settlements in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, granted by the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>
themselves; that the hostages had been given by their own good-will;
that he took by right of war the tribute which conquerors are accustomed
to impose on the conquered; that he had not made war upon the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, but
the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> upon him; that all the states of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> came to attack him, and
had encamped against him; that all their forces had been routed and
beaten by him in a single battle; that if they chose to make a second
trial, he was ready to encounter them again; but if they chose to enjoy
peace, it was unfair to refuse the tribute, which of their own free-will
they had paid up to that time. That the friendship of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>
ought to prove to him an ornament and a safeguard, not a detriment; and
that he sought it with that expectation. But if through the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>
the tribute was to be discontinued, and those who surrendered to be
seduced from him, he would renounce the friendship of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>
no less heartily than he had sought it. As to his leading over a host of
<tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, that he was doing this with a view of securing
himself, not of assaulting <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>: that there was evidence of this, in
that he did not come without being invited, and in that he did not make
war, but merely warded it off. That he had come into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> before the
<tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>. That never before this time did a Roman army go beyond the
frontiers of the province of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>. What [said he] does [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>] desire?
--why come into his [Ariovistus's] domains?--that this was his province
of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, just as that is ours. As it ought not to be pardoned in him, if
he were to make an attack upon our territories; so, likewise, that we
were unjust to obstruct him in his prerogative. As for <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s saying
that the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> had been styled 'brethren' by the senate, he was not so
uncivilized nor so ignorant of affairs, as not to know that the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> in
the very last war with the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe> had neither rendered assistance to
the Romans, nor received any from the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> in the struggles
which the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> had been maintaining with him and with the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>. He
must feel suspicious that <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, though feigning friendship as the
reason for his keeping an army in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>; was keeping it with the view of
crushing him. And that unless he depart, and withdraw his army from
these parts, he shall regard him not as a friend, but as a foe; and
that, even if he should put him to death, he should do what would please
many of the nobles and leading men of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>; he had assurance
of that from themselves through their messengers, and could purchase the
favour and the friendship of them all by his [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s] death. But if he
would depart and resign to him the free possession of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, he would
recompense him with a great reward, and would bring to a close whatever
wars he wished to be carried on, without any trouble or risk to him."</chapter>

<chapter n="XLV">XLV.--Many things were stated by <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> to the effect [to show]: "why he
could not waive the business, and that neither his nor the Roman
people's practice would suffer him to abandon most meritorious allies,
nor did he deem that <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> belonged to Ariovistus rather than to the
<tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>; that the Arverni and the Ruteni had been subdued in war by
Quintus Fabius Maximus, and that the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> had pardoned them and
had not reduced them into a province or imposed a tribute upon them. And
if the most ancient period was to be regarded--then was the sovereignty
of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> most just: if the decree of the senate was
to be observed, then ought <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> to be free, which they [the Romans] had
conquered in war, and had permitted to enjoy its own laws."</chapter>

<chapter n="XLVI">XLVI.--While these things are being transacted in the conference, it was
announced to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> that the cavalry of Ariovistus were approaching
nearer the mound, and were riding up to our men, and casting stones and
weapons at them. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> made an end of his speech and betook himself to
his men; and commanded them that they should by no means return a weapon
upon the enemy. For though he saw that an engagement with the cavalry
would be without any danger to his chosen legion, yet he did not think
proper to engage, lest, after the enemy were routed, it might be said
that they had been ensnared by him under the sanction of a conference.
When it was spread abroad among the common soldiery with what
haughtiness Ariovistus had behaved at the conference, and how he had
ordered the Romans to quit <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and how his cavalry had made an attack
upon our men, and how this had broken off the conference, a much greater
alacrity and eagerness for battle was infused into our army.</chapter>

<chapter n="XLVII">XLVII.--Two days after, Ariovistus sends ambassadors to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, to state
"that he wished to treat with him about those things which had been
begun to be treated of between them, but had not been concluded"; [and
to beg] that "he would either again appoint a day for a conference; or,
if he were not willing to do that, that he would send one of his
[officers] as an ambassador to him." There did not appear to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> any
good reason for holding a conference; and the more so as the day before
the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> could not be restrained from casting weapons at our men. He
thought he should not without great danger send to him as ambassador one
of his [Roman] officers, and should expose him to savage men. It seemed
[therefore] most proper to send to him C. Valerius Procillus, the son of
C. Valerius Caburus, a young man of the highest courage and
accomplishments (whose father had been presented with the freedom of the
city by C. Valerius Flaccus), both on account of his fidelity and on
account of his knowledge of the Gallic language, which Ariovistus, by
long practice, now spoke fluently; and because in his case the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>
would have no motive for committing violence; and [as his colleague] M.
Mettius, who had shared the hospitality of Ariovistus. He commissioned
them to learn what Ariovistus had to say, and to report to him. But when
Ariovistus saw them before him in his camp, he cried out in the presence
of his army, "Why were they come to him? was it for the purpose of
acting as spies?" He stopped them when attempting to speak, and cast
them into chains.</chapter>

<chapter n="XLVIII">XLVIII.--The same day he moved his camp forward and pitched under a hill
six miles from <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s camp. The day following he led his forces past
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s camp, and encamped two miles beyond him; with this design--that
he might cut off <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> from, the corn and provisions which might be
conveyed to him from the <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe> and the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>. For five successive days
from that day, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> drew out his forces before the camp, and put them
in battle order, that, if Ariovistus should be willing to engage in
battle, an opportunity might not be wanting to him. Ariovistus all this
time kept his army in camp: but engaged daily in cavalry skirmishes. The
method of battle in which the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> had practised themselves was this.
There were 6000 horse, and as many very active and courageous foot, one
of whom each of the horse selected out of the whole army for his own
protection. By these [foot] they were constantly accompanied in their
engagements; to these the horse retired; these on any emergency rushed
forward; if any one, upon receiving a very severe wound, had fallen from
his horse, they stood around him: if it was necessary to advance
farther: than usual, or to retreat more rapidly, so great, from
practice, was their swiftness, that, supported by the manes of the
horses, they could keep pace with their speed.</chapter>

<chapter n="XLIX">XLIX.--Perceiving that Ariovistus kept himself in camp, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, that he
might not any longer be cut off from provisions, chose a convenient
position for a camp beyond that place in which the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> had encamped,
at about 600 paces from them, and having drawn up his army in three
lines, marched to that place. He ordered the first and second lines to
be under arms; the third to fortify the camp. This place was distant
from the enemy about 600 paces, as has been stated. Thither Ariovistus
sent light troops, about 16,000 men in number, with all his cavalry;
which forces were to intimidate our men, and hinder them in their
fortification. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> nevertheless, as he had before arranged, ordered
two lines to drive off the enemy: the third to execute the work. The
camp being fortified, he left there two legions and a portion of the
auxiliaries; and led back the other four legions into the larger camp.</chapter>

<chapter n="L">L.--The next day, according to his custom, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> led out his forces
from both camps, and having advanced a little from the larger one, drew
up his line of battle, and gave the enemy an opportunity of fighting.
When he found that they did not even then come out [from their
entrenchments], he led back his army into camp about noon. Then at last
Ariovistus sent part of his forces to attack the lesser camp. The battle
was vigorously maintained on both sides till the evening. At sunset,
after many wounds had been inflicted and received, Ariovistus led back
his forces into camp. When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> inquired of his prisoners, wherefore
Ariovistus did not come to an engagement, he discovered this to be the
reason--that among the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> it was the custom for their matrons to
pronounce from lots and divination whether it were expedient that the
battle should be engaged in or not; that they had said, "that it was not
the will of heaven that the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> should conquer, if they engaged in
battle before the new moon."</chapter>

<chapter n="LI">LI.--The day following, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> left what seemed sufficient as a guard
for both camps; [and then] drew up all the auxiliaries in sight of the
enemy, before the lesser camp, because he was not very powerful in the
number of legionary soldiers, considering the number of the enemy; that
[thereby] he might make use of his auxiliaries for appearance. He
himself, having drawn up his army in three lines, advanced to the camp
of the enemy. Then at last of necessity the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> drew their forces
out of camp, and disposed them canton by canton, at equal distances, the
Harudes, Marcomanni, Tribocci, Vangiones, Nemetes, Sedusii, Suevi; and
surrounded their whole army with their chariots and waggons, that no
hope might be left in flight. On these they placed their women, who,
with dishevelled hair and in tears, entreated the soldiers, as they went
forward to battle, not to deliver them into slavery to the Romans.</chapter>

<chapter n="LII">LII.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> appointed over each legion a lieutenant and a questor, that
every one might have them as witnesses of his valour. He himself began
the battle at the head of the right wing, because he had observed that
part of the enemy to be the least strong. Accordingly our men, upon the
signal being given, vigorously made an attack upon the enemy, and the
enemy so suddenly and rapidly rushed forward, that there was no time for
casting the javelins at them. Throwing aside [therefore] their javelins,
they fought with swords hand to hand. But the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, according to
their custom, rapidly forming a phalanx, sustained the attack of our
swords. There were found very many of our soldiers who leaped upon the
phalanx, and with their hands tore away the shields, and wounded the
enemy from above. Although the army of the enemy was routed on the left
wing and put to flight, they [still] pressed heavily on our men from the
right wing, by the great number of their troops. On observing which, P.
Crassus, a young man, who commanded the cavalry--as he was more
disengaged than those who were employed in the fight--sent the third
line as a relief to our men who were in distress.</chapter>

<chapter n="LIII">LIII.--Thereupon the engagement was renewed, and all the enemy turned
their backs, nor did they cease to flee until they arrived at the river
<place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, about fifty miles from that place. There some few, either relying
on their strength, endeavoured to swim over, or, finding boats, procured
their safety. Among the latter was Ariovistus, who meeting with a small
vessel tied to the bank, escaped in it: our horse pursued and slew all
the rest of them. Ariovistus had two wives, one a Suevan by nation, whom
he had brought with him from home; the other a Norican, the sister of
king Vocion, whom he had married in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, she having been sent [thither
for that purpose] by her brother. Both perished in that flight. Of their
two daughters, one was slain, the other captured. C. Valerius Procillus,
as he was being dragged by his guards in the flight, bound with a triple
chain, fell into the hands of <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> himself, as he was pursuing the
enemy with his cavalry. This circumstance indeed afforded <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> no less
pleasure than the victory itself; because he saw a man of the first rank
in the province of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, his intimate acquaintance and friend, rescued
from the hand of the enemy, and restored to him, and that fortune had
not diminished aught of the joy and exultation [of that day] by his
destruction. He [Procillus] said that in his own presence the lots had
been thrice consulted respecting him, whether he should immediately be
put to death by fire, or be reserved for another time: that by the
favour of the lots he was uninjured. M. Mettius, also, was found and
brought back to him [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>].</chapter>

<chapter n="LIV">LIV.--This battle having been reported beyond the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, the Suevi, who
had come to the banks of that river, began to return home, when the
Ubii, who dwelt nearest to the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, pursuing them, while much alarmed,
slew a great number of them. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> having concluded two very important
wars in one campaign, conducted his army into winter quarters among the
<tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, a little earlier than the season of the year required. He
appointed <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName> over the winter quarters, and set out in person for
Hither <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> to hold the assizes.</chapter></book>



<book num="2"><heading>BOOK II</heading>

<chapter n="I">I.--While <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> was in winter quarters in Hither <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, as we have shown
above, frequent reports were brought to him, and he was also informed by
letters from <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName>, that all the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>, who we have said are a third
part of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, were entering into a confederacy against the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>,
and giving hostages to one another; that the reasons of the confederacy
were these--first, because they feared that, after all [Celtic] <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> was
subdued, our army would be led against them; secondly, because they were
instigated by several of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>; some of whom as [on the one hand]
they had been unwilling that the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> should remain any longer in
<place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, so [on the other] they were dissatisfied that the army of the
<tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> should pass the winter in it, and settle there; and others
of them, from a natural instability and fickleness of disposition, were
anxious for a revolution; [the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> were instigated] by several, also,
because the government in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> was generally seized upon by the more
powerful persons and by those who had the means of hiring troops, and
they could less easily effect this object under our dominion.</chapter>

<chapter n="II">II.--Alarmed by these tidings and letters, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> levied two new legions
in Hither <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and, at the beginning of summer, sent Q. Pedius, his
lieutenant, to conduct them further into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>. He himself, as soon as
there began to be plenty of forage, came to the army. He gives a
commission to the Senones and the other <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> who were neighbours of the
<tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>, to learn what is going on amongst them [_i.e._ the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>], and
inform him of these matters. These all uniformly reported that troops
were being raised, and that an army was being collected in one place.
Then, indeed, he thought that he ought not to hesitate about proceeding
towards them, and having provided supplies, moves his camp, and in about
fifteen days arrives at the territories of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>.</chapter>

<chapter n="III">III.--As he arrived there unexpectedly and sooner than any one
anticipated, the Remi, who are the nearest of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> to [Celtic]
<place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, sent to him Iccius and Antebrogius, [two of] the principal persons
of the state, as their ambassadors: to tell him that they surrendered
themselves and all their possessions to the protection and disposal of
the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>: and that they had neither combined with the rest of
the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>, nor entered into any confederacy against the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>:
and were prepared to give hostages, to obey his commands, to receive him
into their towns, and to aid him with corn and other things; that all
the rest of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> were in arms; and that the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, who dwell on
this side the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, had joined themselves to them; and that so great
was the infatuation of them all that they could not restrain even the
Suessiones, their own brethren and kinsmen, who enjoy the same rights,
and the same laws, and who have one government and one magistracy [in
common] with themselves, from uniting with them.</chapter>

<chapter n="IV">IV.--When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> inquired of them what states were in arms, how powerful
they were, and what they could do in war, he received the following
information: that the greater part of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> were sprung from the
<tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, and that having crossed the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place> at an early period, they had
settled there, on account of the fertility of the country, and had
driven out the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> who inhabited those regions; and that they were the
only people who, in the memory of our fathers, when all <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> was
overrun, had prevented the Teutones and the Cimbri from entering their
territories; the effect of which was that, from the recollection of
those events, they assumed to themselves great authority and haughtiness
in military matters. The Remi said that they had known accurately
everything respecting their number, because, being united to them by
neighbourhood and by alliances, they had learnt what number each state
had in the general council of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> promised for that war. That the
Bellovaci were the most powerful amongst them in valour, influence, and
number of men; that these could muster 100,000 armed men, [and had]
promised 60,000 picked men out of that number, and demanded for
themselves the command of the whole war. That the Suessiones were their
nearest neighbours and possessed a very extensive and fertile country;
that among them, even in our own memory, <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName>, the most powerful
man of all <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, had been king; who had held the government of a great
part of these regions, as well as of Britain; that their king at present
was Galba; that the direction of the whole war was conferred by the
consent of all upon him, on account of his integrity and prudence; that
they had twelve towns; that they had promised 50,000 armed men; and that
the Nervii, who are reckoned the most warlike among them, and are
situated at a very great distance, [had promised] as many; the
Atrebates, 15,000; the Ambiani, 10,000; the Morini, 25,000; the Menapu,
9000; the Caleti, 10,000; the Velocasses and the Veromandui as many; the
Aduatuci, 19,000; that the Condrusi, the Eburones, the Caeraesi, the
Paemani, who are called by the common name of <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, [had promised],
they thought, to the number of 40,000.</chapter>

<chapter n="V">V.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, having encouraged the Remi, and addressed them courteously,
ordered the whole senate to assemble before him, and the children of
their chief men to be brought to him as hostages; all which commands
they punctually performed by the day [appointed]. He, addressing himself
to <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName> the Aeduan, with great earnestness, points out how much it
concerns the republic and their common security, that the forces of the
enemy should be divided, so that it might not be necessary to engage
with so large a number at one time. [He asserts] that this might be
effected if the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> would lead their forces into the territories of
the Bellovaci, and begin to lay waste their country. With these
instructions he dismissed him from his presence. After he perceived that
all the forces of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>, which had been collected in one place,
were approaching towards him, and learnt from the scouts whom he had
sent out, and [also] from the Remi, that they were not then far distant,
he hastened to lead his army over the Aisne, which is on the borders of
the Remi, and there pitched his camp. This position fortified one side
of his camp by the banks of the river, rendered the country which lay in
his rear secure from the enemy, and furthermore ensured that provisions
might without danger be brought to him by the Remi and the rest of the
states. Over that river was a bridge: there he places a guard; and on
the other side of the river he leaves Q. Titurus Sabinus, his
lieutenant, with six cohorts. He orders him to fortify a camp with a
rampart twelve feet in height, and a trench eighteen feet in breadth.</chapter>

<chapter n="VI">VI.--There was a town of the Remi, by name Bibrax, eight miles distant
from this camp. This the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> on their march began to attack with
great vigour. [The assault] was with difficulty sustained for that day.
The <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>' mode of besieging is the same as that of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>: when
after having drawn a large number of men around the whole of the
fortifications, stones have begun to be cast against the wall on all
sides, and the wall has been stript of its defenders, [then], forming a
testudo, they advance to the gates and undermine the wall: which was
easily effected on this occasion; for while so large a number were
casting stones and darts, no one was able to maintain his position upon
the wall. When night had put an end to the assault, Iccius, who was then
in command of the town, one of the Remi, a man of the highest rank and
influence amongst his people, and one of those who had come to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> as
ambassador [to sue] for a peace, sends messengers to him, [to report]
"That, unless assistance were sent to him, he could not hold out any
longer."</chapter>

<chapter n="VII">VII.--Thither immediately after midnight, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, using as guides the
same persons who had come to him as messengers from Iccius, sends some
Numidian and Cretan archers, and some Balearian slingers as a relief to
the townspeople, by whose arrival both a desire to resist together with
the hope of [making good their] defence was infused into the Remi, and,
for the same reason, the hope of gaining the town abandoned the enemy.
Therefore, after staying a short time before the town, and laying waste
the country of the Remi, when all the villages and buildings which they
could approach had been burnt, they hastened with all their forces to
the camp of <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, and encamped within less than two miles [of it]; and
their camp, as was indicated by the smoke and fires, extended more than
eight miles in breadth.</chapter>

<chapter n="VIII">VIII.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> at first determined to decline a battle, as well on
account of the great number of the enemy as their distinguished
reputation for valour: daily, however, in cavalry actions, he strove to
ascertain by frequent trials what the enemy could effect by their
prowess and what our men would dare. When he perceived that our men were
not inferior, as the place before the camp was naturally convenient and
suitable for marshalling an army (since the hill where the camp was
pitched, rising gradually from the plain, extended forward in breadth as
far as the space which the marshalled army could occupy, and had steep
declines of its side in either direction, and gently sloping in front
gradually sank to the plain), on either side of that hill he drew a
cross trench of about four hundred paces, and at the extremities of that
trench built forts, and placed there his military engines, lest, after
he had marshalled his army, the enemy, since they were so powerful in
point of number, should be able to surround his men in the flank, while
fighting. After doing this, and leaving in the camp the two legions
which he had last raised, that, if there should be any occasion, they
might be brought as a reserve, he formed the other six legions in order
of battle before the camp. The enemy, likewise, had drawn up their
forces which they had brought out of the camp.</chapter>

<chapter n="IX">IX.--There was a marsh of no great extent between our army and that of
the enemy. The latter were waiting to see if our men would pass this;
our men, also, were ready in arms to attack them while disordered, if
the first attempt to pass should be made by them. In the meantime battle
was commenced between the two armies by a cavalry action. When neither
army began to pass the marsh, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, upon the skirmishes of the horse
[proving] favourable to our men, led back his forces into the camp. The
enemy immediately hastened from that place to the river Aisne, which it
has been stated was behind our camp. Finding a ford there, they
endeavoured to lead a part of their forces over it; with the design,
that, if they could, they might carry by storm the fort which Q.
Titurius, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s lieutenant, commanded, and might cut off the bridge;
but, if they could not do that, they should lay waste the lands of the
Remi, which were of great use to us in carrying on the war, and might
hinder our men from foraging.</chapter>

<chapter n="X">X.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, being apprised of this by Titurius, leads all his cavalry
and light-armed Numidians, slingers and archers, over the bridge, and
hastens towards them. There was a severe struggle in that place. Our
men, attacking in the river the disordered enemy, slew a great part of
them. By the immense number of their missiles they drove back the rest,
who in a most courageous manner were attempting to pass over their
bodies, and surrounded with their cavalry, and cut to pieces those who
had first crossed the river. The enemy, when they perceived that their
hopes had deceived them both with regard to their taking the town by
storm and also their passing the river, and did not see our men advance
to a more disadvantageous place for the purpose of fighting, and when
provisions began to fail them, having called a council, determined that
it was best for each to return to his country, and resolved to assemble
from all quarters to defend those into whose territories the Romans
should first march an army; that they might contend in their own rather
than in a foreign country, and might enjoy the stores of provisions
which they possessed at home. Together with other causes, this
consideration also led them to that resolution, viz.: that they had
learnt that <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName> and the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> were approaching the territories of
the Bellovaci. And it was impossible to persuade the latter to stay any
longer, or to deter them from conveying succour to their own people.</chapter>

<chapter n="XI">XI.--That matter being determined on, marching out of their camp at the
second watch, with great noise and confusion, in no fixed order, nor
under any command, since each sought for himself the foremost place in
the journey, and hastened to reach home, they made their departure
appear very like a flight. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, immediately learning this through his
scouts, [but] fearing an ambuscade, because he had not yet discovered
for what reason they were departing, kept his army and cavalry within
the camp. At daybreak, the intelligence having been confirmed by the
scouts, he sent forward his cavalry to harass their rear; and gave the
command of it to two of his lieutenants, Q. Pedius, and L. Aurunculeius
Cotta. He ordered T. <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName>, another of his lieutenants, to follow
them closely with three legions. These, attacking their rear, and
pursuing them for many miles, slew a great number of them as they were
fleeing; while those in the rear with whom they had come up, halted, and
bravely sustained the attack of our soldiers; the van, because they
appeared to be removed from danger, and were not restrained by any
necessity or command, as soon as the noise was heard, broke their ranks,
and, to a man, rested their safety in flight. Thus without any risk [to
themselves] our men killed as great a number of them as the length of
the day allowed; and at sunset desisted from the pursuit, and betook
themselves into the camp, as they had been commanded.</chapter>

<chapter n="XII">XII.--On the day following, before the enemy could recover from their
terror and flight, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> led his army into the territories of the
Suessiones, which are next to the Remi, and having accomplished a long
march, hastens to the town named Noviodunum. Having attempted to take it
by storm on his march, because he heard that it was destitute of
[sufficient] defenders, he was not able to carry it by assault, on
account of the breadth of the ditch and the height of the wall, though
few were defending it. Therefore, having fortified the camp, he began to
bring up the vineae, and to provide whatever things were necessary for
the storm. In the meantime, the whole body of the Suessiones, after
their flight, came the next night into the town. The vineae having been
quickly brought up against the town, a mound thrown up, and towers
built, the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, amazed by the greatness of the works, such as they had
neither seen nor heard of before, and struck, also, by the despatch of
the Romans, send ambassadors to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> respecting a surrender, and
succeed in consequence of the Remi requesting that they [the Suessiones]
might be spared.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIII">XIII.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, having received as hostages the first men of the state,
and even the two sons of king Galba himself; and all the arms in the
town having been delivered up, admitted the Suessiones to a surrender,
and led his army against the Bellovaci. Who, when they had conveyed
themselves and all their possessions into the town called Bratuspantium,
and <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> with his army was about five miles distant from that town,
all the old men, going out of the town, began to stretch out their hands
to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, and to intimate by their voice that they would throw
themselves on his protection and power, nor would contend in arms
against the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>. In like manner, when he had come up to the
town, and there pitched his camp, the boys and the women from the wall,
with outstretched hands, after their custom, begged peace from the
Romans.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIV">XIV.--For these <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName> pleads (for after the departure of the
<tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>, having dismissed the troops of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, he had returned to
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>). "The Bellovaci had at all times been in the alliance and
friendship of the Aeduan state; that they had revolted from the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>
and made war upon the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, being urged thereto by their nobles,
who said that the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, reduced to slavery by <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, were suffering
every indignity and insult. That they who had been the leaders of that
plot, because they perceived how great a calamity they had brought upon
the state, had fled into Britain. That not only the Bellovaci, but also
the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe>, entreated him to use his [accustomed] clemency and lenity
towards them [the Bellovaci]: which if he did, he would increase the
influence of the <tribe name="Aedui">Aedui</tribe> among all the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>, by whose succour and
resources they had been accustomed to support themselves whenever any
wars occurred."</chapter>

<chapter n="XV">XV.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> said that on account of his respect for <persName eth="aedui" role="druid">Divitiacus</persName> and the
Aeduans, he would receive them into his protection, and would spare
them; but, because the state was of great influence among the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>,
and pre-eminent in the number of its population, he demanded 600
hostages. When these were delivered, and all the arms in the town
collected, he went from that place into the territories of the Ambiani,
who, without delay, surrendered themselves and all their possessions.
Upon their territories bordered the Nervii, concerning whose character
and customs when <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> inquired he received the following information:
--That "there was no access for merchants to them; that they suffered no
wine and other things tending to luxury to be imported; because they
thought that by their use the mind is enervated and the courage
impaired: that they were a savage people and of great bravery: that they
upbraided and condemned the rest of the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> who had surrendered
themselves to the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> and thrown aside their national courage:
that they openly declared they would neither send ambassadors, nor
accept any condition of peace."</chapter>

<chapter n="XVI">XVI.--After he had made three days' march through their territories, he
discovered from some prisoners, that the river Sambre was not more than
ten miles from his camp: that all the Nervii had stationed themselves on
the other side of that river, and together with the Atrebates and the
Veromandui, their neighbours, were there awaiting the arrival of the
Romans; for they had persuaded both these nations to try the same
fortune of war [as themselves]: that the forces of the Aduatuci were
also expected by them, and were on their march; that they had put their
women, and those who through age appeared useless for war, in a place to
which there was no approach for an army, on account of the marshes.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVII">XVII.--Having learnt these things, he sends forward scouts and
centurions to choose a convenient place for the camp. And as a great
many of the surrounding <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> and other <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, following <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>,
marched with him; some of these, as was afterwards learnt from the
prisoners, having accurately observed, during those days, the army's
method of marching, went by night to the Nervii, and informed them that
a great number of baggage-trains passed between the several legions, and
that there would be no difficulty, when the first legion had come into
the camp, and the other legions were at a great distance, to attack that
legion while under baggage, which being routed, and the baggage-train
seized, it would come to pass that the other legions would not dare to
stand their ground. It added weight also to the advice of those who
reported that circumstance, that the Nervii, from early times, because
they were weak in cavalry (for not even at this time do they attend to
it, but accomplish by their infantry whatever they can), in order that
they might the more easily obstruct the cavalry of their neighbours if
they came upon them for the purpose of plundering, having cut young
trees, and bent them, by means of their numerous branches [extending] on
to the sides, and the quick-briars and thorns springing up between them,
had made these hedges present a fortification like a wall, through which
it was not only impossible to enter, but even to penetrate with the eye.
Since [therefore] the march of our army would be obstructed by these
things, the Nervii thought that the advice ought not to be neglected by
them.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVIII">XVIII.--The nature of the ground which our men had chosen for the camp
was this: A hill, declining evenly from the top, extended to the river
Sambre, which we have mentioned above: from this river there arose a
[second] hill of like ascent, on the other side and opposite to the
former, and open from about 200 paces at the lowest part; but in the
upper part, woody, (so much so) that it was not easy to see through it
into the interior. Within those woods the enemy kept themselves in
concealment; a few troops of horse-soldiers appeared on the open ground,
along the river. The depth of the river was about three feet.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIX">XIX.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, having sent his cavalry on before, followed close after
them with all his forces; but the plan and order of the march was
different from that which the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe> had reported to the Nervii. For as
he was approaching the enemy <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, according to his custom, led on [as
the van] six legions unencumbered by baggage; behind them he had placed
the baggage-trains of the whole army; then the two legions which had
been last raised closed the rear, and were a guard for the baggage-train.
Our horse, with the slingers and archers, having passed the river,
commenced action with the cavalry of the enemy. While they from
time to time betook themselves into the woods to their companions, and
again made an assault out of the wood upon our men, who did not dare to
follow them in their retreat further than the limit to which the plain
and open parts extended, in the meantime the six legions which had
arrived first, having measured out the work, began to fortify the camp.
When the first part of the baggage-train of our army was seen by those
who lay hid in the woods, which had been agreed on among them as the
time for commencing action, as soon as they had arranged their line of
battle and formed their ranks within the woods, and had encouraged one
another, they rushed out suddenly with all their forces and made an
attack upon our horse. The latter being easily routed and thrown into
confusion, the Nervii ran down to the river with such incredible speed
that they seemed to be in the woods, the river, and close upon us almost
at the same time. And with the same speed they hastened up the hill to
our camp and to those who were employed in the works.</chapter>

<chapter n="XX">XX.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had everything to do at one time: the standard to be
displayed, which was the sign when it was necessary to run to arms; the
signal to be given by the trumpet; the soldiers to be called off from
the works; those who had proceeded some distance for the purpose of
seeking materials for the rampart, to be summoned; the order of battle
to be formed; the soldiers to be encouraged; the watchword to be given.
A great part of these arrangements was prevented by the shortness of
time and the sudden approach and charge of the enemy. Under these
difficulties two things proved of advantage; [first] the skill and
experience of the soldiers, because, having been trained by former
engagements, they could suggest to themselves what ought to be done, as
conveniently as receive information from others; and [secondly] that
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had forbidden his several lieutenants to depart from the works
and their respective legions, before the camp was fortified. These, on
account of the near approach and the speed of the enemy, did not then
wait for any command from <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, but of themselves executed whatever
appeared proper.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXI">XXI.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, having given the necessary orders, hastened to and fro
into whatever quarter fortune carried him to animate the troops, and
came to the tenth legion. Having encouraged the soldiers with no further
speech than that "they should keep up the remembrance of their wonted
valour, and not be confused in mind, but valiantly sustain the assault
of the enemy"; as the latter were not farther from them than the
distance to which a dart could be cast, he gave the signal for
commencing battle. And having gone to another quarter for the purpose of
encouraging [the soldiers], he finds them fighting. Such was the
shortness of the time, and so determined was the mind of the enemy on
fighting, that time was wanting not only for affixing the military
insignia, but even for putting on the helmets and drawing off the covers
from the shields. To whatever part any one by chance came from the works
(in which he had been employed), and whatever standards he saw first, at
these he stood, lest in seeking his own company he should lose the time
for fighting.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXII">XXII.--The army having been marshalled, rather as the nature of the
ground and the declivity of the hill and the exigency of the time, than
as the method and order of military matters required; whilst the legions
in the different places were withstanding the enemy, some in one
quarter, some in another, and the view was obstructed by the very thick
hedges intervening, as we have before remarked, neither could proper
reserves be posted, nor could the necessary measures be taken in each
part, nor could all the commands be issued by one person. Therefore, in
such an unfavourable state of affairs, various events of fortune
followed.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIII">XXIII.--The soldiers of the ninth and tenth legions, as they had been
stationed on the left part of the army, casting their weapons, speedily
drove the Atrebates (for that division had been opposed to them), who
were breathless with running and fatigue, and worn out with wounds, from
the higher ground into the river; and following them as they were
endeavouring to pass it, slew with their swords a great part of them
while impeded (therein). They themselves did not hesitate to pass the
river; and having advanced to a disadvantageous place, when the battle
was renewed, they [nevertheless] again put to flight the enemy, who had
returned and were opposing them. In like manner, in another quarter two
different legions, the eleventh and the eighth, having routed the
Veromandui, with whom they had engaged, were fighting from the higher
ground upon the very banks of the river. But, almost the whole camp on
the front and on the left side being then exposed, since the twelfth
legion was posted in the right wing, and the seventh at no great
distance from it, all the Nervii, in a very close body, with
Boduognatus, who held the chief command, as their leader, hastened
towards that place; and part of them began to surround the legions on
their unprotected flank, part to make for the highest point of the
encampment.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIV">XXIV.--At the same time our horsemen, and light-armed infantry, who had
been with those who, as I have related, were routed by the first assault
of the enemy, as they were betaking themselves into the camp, met the
enemy face to face, and again sought flight into another quarter; and
the camp-followers who from the Decuman Gate and from the highest ridge
of the hill had seen our men pass the river as victors, when, after
going out for the purposes of plundering, they looked back and saw the
enemy parading in our camp, committed themselves precipitately to
flight; at the same time there arose the cry and shout of those who came
with the baggage-train; and they (affrighted) were carried some one way,
some another. By all these circumstances the cavalry of the Treviri were
much alarmed (whose reputation for courage is extraordinary among the
<tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, and who had come to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, being sent by their state as
auxiliaries), and, when they saw our camp filled with a large number of
the enemy, the legions hard pressed and almost held surrounded, the
camp-retainers, horsemen, slingers, and Numidians fleeing on all sides
divided and scattered, they, despairing of our affairs, hastened home,
and related to their state that the Romans were routed and conquered,
[and] that the enemy were in possession of their camp and baggage-train.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXV">XXV.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> proceeded, after encouraging the tenth legion, to the right
wing; where he perceived that his men were hard pressed, and that in
consequence of the standards of the twelfth legion being collected
together in one place, the crowded soldiers were a hindrance to
themselves in the fight; that all the centurions of the fourth cohort
were slain, and the standard-bearer killed, the standard itself lost,
almost all the centurions of the other cohorts either wounded or slain,
and among them the chief centurion of the legion, P. Sextius Baculus, a
very valiant man, who was so exhausted by many and severe wounds, that
he was already unable to support himself; he likewise perceived that the
rest were slackening their efforts, and that some, deserted by those in
the rear, were retiring from the battle and avoiding the weapons; that
the enemy [on the other hand], though advancing from the lower ground,
were not relaxing in front, and were [at the same time] pressing hard on
both flanks; he also perceived that the affair was at a crisis, and that
there was not any reserve which could be brought up; having therefore
snatched a shield from one of the soldiers in the rear (for he himself
had come without a shield), he advanced to the front of the line, and
addressing the centurions by name, and encouraging the rest of the
soldiers, he ordered them to carry forward the standards, and extend the
companies, that they might the more easily use their swords. On his
arrival, as hope was brought to the soldiers and their courage restored,
whilst every one for his own part, in the sight of his general, desired
to exert his utmost energy, the impetuosity of the enemy was a little
checked.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVI">XXVI.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, when he perceived that the seventh legion, which stood
close by him, was also hard pressed by the enemy, directed the tribunes
of the soldiers to effect a junction of the legions gradually, and make
their charge upon the enemy with a double front; which having been done,
since they brought assistance the one to the other, nor feared lest
their rear should be surrounded by the enemy, they began to stand their
ground more boldly, and to fight more courageously. In the meantime, the
soldiers of the two legions which had been in the rear of the army, as a
guard for the baggage-train, upon the battle being reported to them,
quickened their pace, and were seen by the enemy on the top of the hill;
and <persName eth="roman" role="lieutenant">Titus Labienus</persName>, having gained possession of the camp of the enemy,
and observed from the higher ground what was going on in our camp, sent
the tenth legion as a relief to our men, who, when they had learnt from
the flight of the horse and the sutlers in what position the affair was,
and in how great danger the camp and the legion and the commander were
involved, left undone nothing [which tended] to despatch.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVI">XXVI.--By their arrival, so great a change of matters was made, that our
men, even those who had fallen down exhausted with wounds, leant on
their shields, and renewed the fight: then the camp-retainers, though
unarmed, seeing the enemy completely dismayed, attacked [them though]
armed; the horsemen too, that they might by their valour blot out the
disgrace of their flight, thrust themselves before the legionary
soldiers in all parts of the battle. But the enemy, even in the last
hope of safety, displayed such great courage that when the foremost of
them had fallen, the next stood upon them prostrate, and fought from
their bodies; when these were overthrown, and their corpses heaped up
together, those who survived cast their weapons against our men
[thence], as from a mound, and returned our darts which had fallen
between [the armies]; so that it ought not to be concluded, that men of
such great courage had injudiciously dared to pass a very broad river,
ascend very high banks, and come up to a very disadvantageous place;
since their greatness of spirit had rendered these actions easy,
although in themselves very difficult.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVIII">XXVIII.--This battle being ended, and the nation and name of the Nervii
being almost reduced to annihilation, their old men, whom together with
the boys and women we have stated to have been collected together in the
fenny places and marshes, on this battle having been reported to them,
since they were convinced that nothing was an obstacle to the
conquerors, and nothing safe to the conquered, sent ambassadors to
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> by the consent of all who remained, and surrendered themselves to
him; and in recounting the calamity of their state, said that their
senators were reduced from 600 to three; that from 60,000 men they [were
reduced] to scarcely 500 who could bear arms; whom <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, that he might
appear to use compassion towards the wretched and the suppliant, most
carefully spared; and ordered them to enjoy their own territories and
towns, and commanded their neighbours that they should restrain
themselves and their dependants from offering injury or outrage [to
them].</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIX">XXIX.--When the Aduatuci, of whom we have written above, were coming
with all their forces to the assistance of the Nervii, upon this battle
being reported to them, they returned home after they were on the march;
deserting all their towns and forts, they conveyed together all their
possessions into one town, eminently fortified by nature. While this
town had on all sides around it very high rocks and precipices, there
was left on one side a gently ascending approach, of not more than 200
feet in width; which place they had fortified with a very lofty double
wall: besides, they had placed stones of great weight and sharpened
stakes upon the walls. They were descended from the Cimbri and Teutones,
who, when they were marching into our province and <place region="italy">Italy</place>, having
deposited on this side the river <place river="rhine">Rhine</place> such of their baggage-trains as
they could not drive or convey with them, left 6000 of their men as a
guard and defence for them. These having, after the destruction of their
countrymen, been harassed for many years by their neighbours, while one
time they waged war offensively, and at another resisted it when waged
against them, concluded a peace with the consent of all, and chose this
place as their settlement.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXX">XXX.--And on the first arrival of our army they made frequent sallies
from the town, and contended with our men in trifling skirmishes:
afterwards, when hemmed in by a rampart of twelve feet [in height], and
fifteen miles in circuit, they kept themselves within the town. When,
vineae having been brought up and a mound raised, they observed that a
tower also was being built at a distance, they at first began to mock
the Romans from their wall, and to taunt them with the following
speeches. "For what purpose was so vast a machine constructed at so
great a distance?" "With what hands," or "with what strength did they,
especially [as they were] men of such very small stature" (for our
shortness of stature, in comparison with the great size of their bodies,
is generally a subject of much contempt to the men of Gaul), "trust to
place against their walls a tower of such great weight."</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXI">XXXI.--But when they saw that it was being moved, and was approaching
their walls, startled by the new and unaccustomed sight, they sent
ambassadors to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> [to treat] about peace; who spoke in the following
manner: "That they did not believe the Romans waged war without divine
aid, since they were able to move forward machines of such a height with
so great speed, and thus fight from close quarters: that they resigned
themselves and all their possessions to [<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s] disposal: that they
begged and earnestly entreated one thing, viz., that if perchance,
agreeably to his clemency and humanity, which they had heard of from
others, he should resolve that the Aduatuci were to be spared, he would
not deprive them of their arms; that all their neighbours were enemies
to them and envied their courage, from whom they could not defend
themselves if their arms were delivered up: that it was better for them,
if they should be reduced to that state, to suffer any fate from the
<tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, than to be tortured to death by those among whom they had
been accustomed to rule."</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXII">XXXII.--To these things <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> replied, "That he, in accordance with his
custom, rather than owing to their desert, should spare the state, if
they should surrender themselves before the battering-ram should touch
the wall; but that there was no condition of surrender, except upon
their arms being delivered up; that he should do to them that which he
had done in the case of the Nervii, and would command their neighbours
not to offer any injury to those who had surrendered to the Roman
people." The matter being reported to their countrymen, they said that
they would execute his commands. Having cast a very large quantity of
their arms from the wall into the trench which was before the town, so
that the heaps of arms almost equalled the top of the wall and the
rampart, and nevertheless having retained and concealed, as we
afterwards discovered, about a third part in the town, the gates were
opened, and they enjoyed peace for that day.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXIII">XXXIII.--Towards evening <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> ordered the gates to be shut, and the
soldiers to go out of the town, lest the townspeople should receive any
injury from them by night. They [the Aduatuci], by a design before
entered into, as we afterwards understood, because they believed that,
as a surrender had been made, our men would dismiss their guards, or at
least would keep watch less carefully, partly with those arms which they
had retained and concealed, partly with shields made of bark or
interwoven wickers, which they had hastily covered over with skins (as
the shortness of time required) in the third watch, suddenly made a
sally from the town with all their forces [in that direction] in which
the ascent to our fortifications seemed the least difficult. The signal
having been immediately given by fires, as <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had previously
commanded, a rush was made thither [_i.e._ by the Roman soldiers] from
the nearest fort; and the battle was fought by the enemy as vigorously
as it ought to be fought by brave men, in the last hope of safety, in a
disadvantageous place, and against those who were throwing their weapons
from a rampart and from towers; since all hope of safety depended on
their courage alone. About 4000 of the men having been slain, the rest
were forced back into the town. The day after, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, after breaking
open the gates, which there was no one then to defend, and sending in
our soldiers, sold the whole spoil of that town. The number of 53,000
persons was reported to him by those who had bought them.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXIV">XXXIV.--At the same time he was informed by P. Crassus, whom he had sent
with one legion against the Veneti, the Unelli, the Osismii, the
Curiosolitae, the Sesuvii, the Aulerci, and the Rhedones, which are
maritime states, and touch upon the [Atlantic] ocean, that all these
nations were brought under the dominion and power of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXV">XXXV.--These things being achieved, [and] all <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> being subdued, so
high an opinion of this war was spread among the barbarians, that
ambassadors were sent to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> by those nations who dwelt beyond the
<place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, to promise that they would give hostages and execute his
commands. Which embassies <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, because he was hastening into <place region="italy">Italy</place>
and Illyricum, ordered to return to him at the beginning of the
following summer. He himself, having led his legions into winter-quarters
among the Carnutes, the Andes, and the Turones, which states
were close to those regions in which he had waged war, set out for
<place region="italy">Italy</place>; and a thanksgiving of fifteen days was decreed for those
achievements, upon receiving <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s letter; [an honour] which before
that time had been conferred on none.</chapter></book>



<book num="3"><heading>BOOK III</heading>

<chapter n="I">I.--When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> was setting out for <place region="italy">Italy</place>, he sent Servius Galba with
the twelfth legion and part of the cavalry against the Nantuates, the
Veragri, and Seduni, who extend from the territories of the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>,
and the lake of <place settlement="geneva">Geneva</place>, and the river <place river="rhone">Rhone</place> to the top of the <place mountain="Alps">Alps</place>. The
reason for sending him was, that he desired that the pass along the
<place mountain="Alps">Alps</place>, through which [the Roman] merchants had been accustomed to travel
with great danger, and under great imposts, should be opened. He
permitted him, if he thought it necessary, to station the legion in
these places, for the purpose of wintering. Galba having fought some
successful battles, and stormed several of their forts, upon ambassadors
being sent to him from all parts and hostages given and a peace
concluded, determined to station two cohorts among the Nantuates, and to
winter in person with the other cohorts of that legion in a village of
the Veragri, which is called Octodurus; and this village being situated
in a valley, with a small plain annexed to it, is bounded on all sides
by very high mountains. As this village was divided into two parts by a
river, he granted one part of it to the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, and assigned the other,
which had been left by them unoccupied, to the cohorts to winter in. He
fortified this [latter] part with a rampart and a ditch.</chapter>

<chapter n="II">II.--When several days had elapsed in winter quarters, and he had
ordered corn to be brought in, he was suddenly informed by his scouts
that all the people had gone off in the night from that part of the town
which he had given up to the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, and that the mountains which hung
over it were occupied by a very large force of the Sedani and Veragri.
It had happened for several reasons that the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> suddenly formed the
design of renewing the war and cutting off that legion. First, because
they despised a single legion, on account of its small number, and that
not quite full (two cohorts having been detached, and several
individuals being absent, who had been despatched for the purpose of
seeking provision); then, likewise, because they thought that on account
of the disadvantageous character of the situation, even their first
attack could not be sustained [by us] when they would rush from the
mountains into the valley, and discharge their weapons upon us. To this
was added, that they were indignant that their children were torn from
them under the title of hostages, and they were persuaded that the
Romans designed to seize upon the summits of the <place mountain="Alps">Alps</place>, and unite those
parts to the neighbouring province [of Gaul], not only to secure the
passes, but also as a constant possession.</chapter>

<chapter n="III">III.--Having received these tidings, Galba, since the works of the
winter quarters and the fortifications were not fully completed, nor was
sufficient preparation made with regard to corn and other provisions
(since, as a surrender had been made, and hostages received, he had
thought he need entertain no apprehension of a war), speedily summoning
a council, began to anxiously inquire their opinions. In which council,
since so much sudden danger had happened contrary to the general
expectation, and almost all the higher places were seen already covered
with a multitude of armed men, nor could [either] troops come to their
relief, or provisions be brought in, as the passes were blocked up [by
the enemy]; safety being now nearly despaired of, some opinions of this
sort were delivered; that, "leaving their baggage, and making a sally,
they should hasten away for safety by the same routes by which they had
come thither." To the greater part, however, it seemed best, reserving
that measure to the last, to await the issue of the matter, and to
defend the camp.</chapter>

<chapter n="IV">IV.--A short time only having elapsed, so that time was scarcely given
for arranging and executing those things which they had determined on,
the enemy, upon the signal being given, rushed down [upon our men] from
all parts, and discharged stones and darts upon our rampart. Our men at
first, while their strength was fresh, resisted bravely, nor did they
cast any weapon ineffectually from their higher station. As soon as any
part of the camp, being destitute of defenders, seemed to be hard
pressed, thither they ran, and brought assistance. But they were
over-matched in this, that the enemy when wearied by the long continuance
of the battle, went out of the action, and others with fresh strength
came in their place; none of which things could be done by our men, owing
to the smallness of their number; and not only was permission not given
to the wearied [Roman] to retire from the fight, but not even to the
wounded [was liberty granted] to quit the post where he had been
stationed, and recover.</chapter>

<chapter n="V">V.--When they had now been fighting for more than six hours, without
cessation, and not only strength, but even weapons were failing our men,
and the enemy were pressing on more rigorously, and had begun to
demolish the rampart and to fill up the trench, while our men were
becoming exhausted, and the matter was now brought to the last
extremity, P. Sextius Baculus, a centurion of the first rank, whom we
have related to have been disabled by severe wounds in the engagement
with the Nervii, and also C. Volusenus, a tribune of the soldiers, a man
of great skill and valour, hasten to Galba, and assure him that the only
hope of safety lay in making a sally, and trying the last resource.
Whereupon, assembling the centurions, he quickly gives orders to the
soldiers to discontinue the fight a short time, and only collect the
weapons flung [at them], and recruit themselves after their fatigue, and
afterwards, upon the signal being given, sally forth from the camp, and
place in their valour all their hope of safety.</chapter>

<chapter n="VI">VI.--They do what they were ordered; and, making a sudden sally from all
the gates [of the camp], leave the enemy the means neither of knowing
what was taking place, nor of collecting themselves. Fortune thus taking
a turn, [our men] surround on every side, and slay those who had
entertained the hope of gaining the camp, and having killed more than
the third part of an army of more than 30,000 men (which number of the
barbarians it appeared certain had come up to our camp), put to flight
the rest when panic-stricken, and do not suffer them to halt even upon
the higher grounds. All the forces of the enemy being thus routed, and
stripped of their arms, [our men] betake themselves to their camp and
fortifications. Which battle being finished, inasmuch as Galba was
unwilling to tempt fortune again, and remembered that he had come into
winter quarters with one design, and saw that he had met with a
different state of affairs; chiefly however urged by the want of corn
and provision, having the next day burned all the buildings of that
village, he hastens to return into the province; and as no enemy opposed
or hindered his march, he brought the legion safe into the [country of
the] Nantuates, thence into [that of] the <tribe name="allobroges">Allobroges</tribe>, and there
wintered.</chapter>

<chapter n="VII">VII.--These things being achieved, while <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had every reason to
suppose that <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> was reduced to a state of tranquillity, the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>
being overcome, the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> expelled, the Seduni among the <place mountain="Alps">Alps</place>
defeated, and when he had, therefore, in the beginning of winter, set
out for Illyricum, as he wished to visit those nations, and acquire a
knowledge of their countries, a sudden war sprang up in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>. The
occasion of that war was this: P. Crassus, a young man, had taken up his
winter quarters with the seventh legion among the Andes, who border upon
the [Atlantic] ocean. He, as there was a scarcity of corn in those
parts, sent out some officers of cavalry and several military tribunes
amongst the neighbouring states, for the purpose of procuring corn and
provision; in which number T. Terrasidius was sent amongst the Esubii;
M. Trebius Gallus amongst the Curiosolitae; Q. Velanius, with T. Silius,
amongst the Veneti.</chapter>

<chapter n="VIII">VIII.--The influence of this state is by far the most considerable of
any of the countries on the whole sea coast, because the Veneti both
have a very great number of ships, with which they have been accustomed
to sail to Britain, and [thus] excel the rest in their knowledge and
experience of nautical affairs; and as only a few ports lie scattered
along that stormy and open sea, of which they are in possession, they
hold as tributaries almost all those who are accustomed to traffic in
that sea. With them arose the beginning [of the revolt] by their
detaining Silius and Velanius; for they thought that they should recover
by their means the hostages which they had given to Crassus. The
neighbouring people, led on by their influence (as the measures of the
<tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> are sudden and hasty), detain Trebius and Terrasidius for the same
motive; and quickly sending ambassadors, by means of their leading men,
they enter into a mutual compact to do nothing except by general
consent, and abide the same issue of fortune; and they solicit the other
states to choose rather to continue in that liberty which they had
received from their ancestors, than endure slavery under the Romans. All
the sea coast being quickly brought over to their sentiments, they send
a common embassy to P. Crassus [to say], "If he wished to receive back
his officers, let him send back to them their hostages."</chapter>

<chapter n="IX">IX.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, being informed of these things by Crassus, since he was so
far distant himself, orders ships of war to be built in the meantime on
the river Loire, which flows into the ocean; rowers to be raised from
the province; sailors and pilots to be provided. These matters being
quickly executed, he himself, as soon as the season of the year permits,
hastens to the army. The Veneti, and the other states also, being
informed of <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s arrival, when they reflected how great a crime they
had committed, in that the ambassadors (a character which had amongst
all nations ever been sacred and inviolable) had by them been detained
and thrown into prison, resolve to prepare for a war in proportion to
the greatness of their danger, and especially to provide those things
which appertain to the service of a navy; with the greater confidence,
inasmuch as they greatly relied on the nature of their situation. They
knew that the passes by land were cut off by estuaries, that the
approach by sea was most difficult, by reason of our ignorance of the
localities, [and] the small number of the harbours, and they trusted
that our army would not be able to stay very long among them, on account
of the insufficiency of corn; and again, even if all these things should
turn out contrary to their expectation, yet they were very powerful in
their navy. They, well understood that the Romans neither had any number
of ships, nor were acquainted with the shallows, the harbours, or the
islands of those parts where they would have to carry on the war; and
that navigation was very different in a narrow sea from what it was in
the vast and open ocean. Having come to this resolution, they fortify
their towns, convey corn into them from the country parts, bring
together as many ships as possible to Venetia, where it appeared <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>
would at first carry on the war. They unite to themselves as allies for
that war, the Osismii, the Lexovii, the Nannetes, the Ambiliati, the
Morini, the Diablintes, and the Menapii; and send for auxiliaries from
Britain, which is situated over against those regions.</chapter>

<chapter n="X">X.--There were these difficulties which we have mentioned above, in
carrying on the war, but many things, nevertheless, urged <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> to that
war; the open insult offered to the state in the detention of the Roman
knights, the rebellion raised after surrendering, the revolt after
hostages were given, the confederacy of so many states, but principally,
lest if [the conduct of] this part was overlooked, the other nations
should think that the same thing was permitted them. Wherefore, since he
reflected that almost all the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> were fond of revolution, and easily
and quickly excited to war; that all men likewise, by nature, love
liberty and hate the condition of slavery, he thought he ought to divide
and more widely distribute his army, before more states should join the
confederation.</chapter>

<chapter n="XI">XI.--He therefore sends T. Labienus, his lieutenant, with the cavalry to
the Treviri, who are nearest to the river <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>. He charges him to visit
the Remi and the other Belgians, and to keep them in their allegiance
and repel the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> (who were said to have been summoned by the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>
to their aid) if they attempted to cross the river by force in their
ships. He orders P. Crassus to proceed into <place region="aquitania">Aquitania</place> with twelve
legionary cohorts and a great number of the cavalry, lest auxiliaries
should be sent into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> by these states, and such great nations be
united. He sends Q. Titurius Sabinus, his lieutenant, with three
legions, among the Unelli, the Curiosolitae, and the Lexovii, to take
care that their forces should be kept separate from the rest. He
appoints D. Brutus, a young man, over the fleet and those Gallic vessels
which he had ordered to be furnished by the Pictones and the Santoni,
and the other provinces which remained at peace; and commands him to
proceed towards the Veneti, as soon as he could. He himself hastens
thither with the land forces.</chapter>

<chapter n="XII">XII.--The sites of their towns were generally such that, being placed on
extreme points [of land] and on promontories, they neither had an
approach by land when the tide had rushed in from the main ocean, which
always happens twice in the space of twelve hours; nor by ships,
because, upon the tide ebbing again, the ships were likely to be dashed
upon the shoals. Thus, by either circumstance, was the storming of their
towns rendered difficult; and if at any time perchance the Veneti,
overpowered by the greatness of our works (the sea having been excluded
by a mound and large dams, and the latter being made almost equal in
height to the walls of the town), had begun to despair of their
fortunes, bringing up a large number of ships, of which they had a very
great quantity, they carried off all their property and betook
themselves to the nearest towns; there they again defended themselves by
the same advantages of situation. They did this the more easily during a
great part of the summer, because our ships were kept back by storms,
and the difficulty of sailing was very great in that vast and open sea,
with its strong tides and its harbours far apart and exceedingly few in
number.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIII">XIII.--For their ships were built and equipped after this manner. The
keels were somewhat flatter than those of our ships, whereby they could
more easily encounter the shallows and the ebbing of the tide: the prows
were raised very high, and in like manner the sterns were adapted to the
force of the waves and storms [which they were formed to sustain]. The
ships were built wholly of oak, and designed to endure any force and
violence whatever; the benches, which were made of planks a foot in
breadth, were fastened by iron spikes of the thickness of a man's thumb;
the anchors were secured fast by iron chains instead of cables, and for
sails they used skins and thin dressed leather. These [were used] either
through their want of canvas and their ignorance of its application, or
for this reason, which is more probable, that they thought that such
storms of the ocean, and such violent gales of wind could not be
resisted by sails, nor ships of such great burden be conveniently enough
managed by them. The encounter of our fleet with these ships was of such
a nature that our fleet excelled in speed alone, and the plying of the
oars; other things, considering the nature of the place [and] the
violence of the storms, were more suitable and better adapted on their
side; for neither could our ships injure theirs with their beaks (so
great was their strength), nor on account of their height was a weapon
easily cast up to them; and for the same reason they were less readily
locked in by rocks. To this was added, that whenever a storm began to
rage and they ran before the wind, they both could weather the storm
more easily and heave to securely in the shallows, and when left by the
tide feared nothing from rocks and shelves: the risk of all which things
was much to be dreaded by our ships.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIV">XIV.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, after taking many of their towns, perceiving that so much
labour was spent in vain and that the flight of the enemy could not be
prevented on the capture of their towns, and that injury could not be
done them, he determined to wait for his fleet. As soon as it came up
and was first seen by the enemy, about 220 of their ships, fully
equipped and appointed with every kind of [naval] implement, sailed
forth from the harbour, and drew up opposite to ours; nor did it appear
clear to Brutus, who commanded the fleet, or to the tribunes of the
soldiers and the centurions, to whom the several ships were assigned,
what to do, or what system of tactics to adopt; for they knew that
damage could not be done by their beaks; and that, although turrets were
built [on their decks], yet the height of the stems of the barbarian
ships exceeded these; so that weapons could not be cast up from [our]
lower position with sufficient effect, and those cast by the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> fell
the more forcibly upon us. One thing provided by our men was of great
service, [viz.] sharp hooks inserted into and fastened upon poles, of a
form not unlike the hooks used in attacking town walls. When the ropes
which fastened the sail-yards to the masts were caught by them and
pulled, and our vessel vigorously impelled with the oars, they [the
ropes] were severed; and when they were cut away, the yards necessarily
fell down; so that as all the hope of the Gallic vessels depended on
their sails and rigging, upon these being cut away, the entire
management of the ships was taken from them at the same time. The rest
of the contest depended on courage; in which our men decidedly had the
advantage; and the more so because the whole action was carried on in
the sight of <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> and the entire army; so that no act, a little more
valiant than ordinary, could pass unobserved, for all the hills and
higher grounds, from which there was a near prospect of the sea, were
occupied by our army.</chapter>

<chapter n="XV">XV.--The sail-yards [of the enemy], as we have said, being brought down,
although two and [in some cases] three ships [of theirs] surrounded each
one [of ours], the soldiers strove with the greatest energy to board the
ships of the enemy: and, after the barbarians observed this taking
place, as a great many of their ships were beaten, and as no relief for
that evil could be discovered, they hastened to seek safety in flight.
And, having now turned their vessels to that quarter in which the wind
blew, so great a calm and lull suddenly arose, that they could not move
out of their place, which circumstance, truly, was exceedingly opportune
for finishing the business; for our men gave chase and took them one by
one, so that very few out of all the number, [and those] by the
intervention of night, arrived at the land, after the battle had lasted
almost from the fourth hour till sunset.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVI">XVI.--By this battle the war with the Veneti and the whole of the sea
coast was finished; for both all the youth, and all, too, of more
advanced age, in whom there was any discretion or rank, had assembled in
that battle; and they had collected in that one place whatever naval
forces they had anywhere; and when these were lost, the survivors had no
place to retreat to, nor means of defending their towns. They
accordingly surrendered themselves and all their possessions to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>,
on whom <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> thought that punishment should be inflicted the more
severely, in order that for the future the rights of ambassadors might
be more carefully respected, by barbarians: having, therefore, put to
death all their senate, he sold the rest for slaves.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVII">XVII.--While these things are going on amongst the Veneti, Q. Titurius
Sabinus with those troops which he had received from <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, arrives in
the territories of the Unelli. Over these people Viridovix ruled, and
held the chief command of all those states which had revolted: from
which he had collected a large and powerful army. And in those few days,
the Aulerci and the Sexovii, having slain their senate because they
would not consent to be promoters of the war, shut their gates [against
us] and united themselves to Viridovix; a great multitude besides of
desperate men and robbers assembled out of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> from all quarters, whom
the hope of plundering and the love of fighting had called away from
husbandry and their daily labour. Sabinus kept himself within his camp,
which was in a position convenient for everything; while Viridovix
encamped over against him at a distance of two miles, and daily bringing
out his forces, gave him an opportunity of fighting; so that Sabinus had
now not only come into contempt with the enemy, but also was somewhat
taunted by the speeches of our soldiers; and furnished so great a
suspicion of his cowardice that the enemy presumed to approach even to
the very rampart of our camp. He adopted this conduct for the following
reason: because he did not think that a lieutenant ought to engage in
battle with so great a force, especially while he who held the chief
command was absent, except on advantageous ground or some favourable
circumstance presented itself.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVIII">XVIII.--After having established this suspicion of his cowardice, he
selected a certain suitable and crafty <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, who was one of those whom
he had with him as auxiliaries. He induces him by great gifts and
promises to go over to the enemy; and informs [him] of what he wished to
be done. Who, when he arrives amongst them as a deserter, lays before
them the fears of the Romans; and informs them by what difficulties
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> himself was harassed, and that the matter was not far removed
from this--that Sabinus would the next night privately draw off his army
out of the camp and set forth to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, for the purpose of carrying
[him] assistance, which, when they heard, they all cry out together that
an opportunity of successfully conducting their enterprise ought not to
be thrown away; that they ought to go to the [Roman] camp. Many things
persuaded the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> to this measure; the delay of Sabinus during the
previous days; the positive assertion of the [pretended] deserter; want
of provisions, for a supply of which they had not taken the requisite
precautions; the hope springing from the Venetic war; and [also] because
in most cases men willingly believe what they wish. Influenced by these
things, they do not discharge Viridovix and the other leaders from the
council, before they gained permission from them to take up arms and
hasten to [our] camp; which being granted, rejoicing as if victory were
fully certain, they collected faggots and brushwood, with which to fill
up the Roman trenches, and hasten to the camp.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIX">XIX.--The situation of the camp was a rising ground, gently sloping from
the bottom for about a mile. Thither they proceeded with great speed (in
order that as little time as possible might be given to the Romans to
collect and arm themselves), and arrived quite out of breath. Sabinus
having encouraged his men, gives them the signal, which they earnestly
desired. While the enemy were encumbered by reason of the burdens which
they were carrying, he orders a sally to be suddenly made from two gates
[of the camp]. It happened, by the advantage of situation, by the
unskilfulness and the fatigue of the enemy, by the valour of our
soldiers, and their experience in former battles, that they could not
stand one attack of our men, and immediately turned their backs: and our
men with full vigour followed them while disordered, and slew a great
number of them; the horse pursuing the rest, left but few, who escaped
by flight. Thus at the same time, Sabinus was informed of the naval
battle and <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> of victory gained by Sabinus; and all the states
immediately surrendered themselves to Titurius: for as the temper of the
<tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> is impetuous and ready to undertake wars, so their mind is weak,
and by no means resolute in enduring calamities.</chapter>

<chapter n="XX">XX.--About the same time, P. Crassus, when he had arrived in <place region="aquitania">Aquitania</place>
(which, as has been before said, both from its extent of territory and
the great number of its people, is to be reckoned a third part of Gaul),
understanding that he was to wage war in these parts, where a few years
before L. Valerius Praeconinus, the lieutenant, had been killed, and his
army routed, and from which L. Manilius, the proconsul, had fled with
the loss of his baggage, he perceived that no ordinary care must be used
by him. Wherefore, having provided corn, procured auxiliaries and
cavalry, [and] having summoned by name many valiant men from Tolosa,
Carcaso, and Narbo, which are the states of the province of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, that
border on these regions <place region="aquitania">[Aquitania]</place>, he led his army into the
territories of the Sotiates. On his arrival being known, the Sotiates
having brought together great forces and [much] cavalry, in which their
strength principally lay, and assailing our army on the march, engaged
first in a cavalry action, then when their cavalry was routed, and our
men pursuing, they suddenly display their infantry forces, which they
had placed in ambuscade in a valley. These attacked our men [while]
disordered, and renewed the fight.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXI">XXI.--The battle was long and vigorously contested, since the Sotiates,
relying on their former victories, imagined that the safety of the whole
of <place region="aquitania">Aquitania</place> rested on their valour; [and] our men, on the other hand,
desired it might be seen what they could accomplish without their
general and without the other legions, under a very young commander; at
length the enemy, worn out with wounds, began to turn their backs, and a
great number of them being slain, Crassus began to besiege the
[principal] town of the Sotiates on his march. Upon their valiantly
resisting, he raised vineae and turrets. They at one time attempting a
sally, at another forming mines to our rampart and vineae (at which the
<tribe name="aquitani">Aquitani</tribe> are eminently skilled, because in many places amongst them
there are copper mines); when they perceived that nothing could be
gained by these operations through the perseverance of our men, they
send ambassadors to Crassus, and entreat him to admit them to a
surrender. Having obtained it, they, being ordered to deliver up their
arms, comply.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXII">XXII.--And while the attention of our men is engaged in that matter, in
another part Adcantuannus, who held the chief command, with 600 devoted
followers, whom they call soldurii (the conditions of whose association
are these,--that they enjoy all the conveniences of life with those to
whose friendship they have devoted themselves: if anything calamitous
happen to them, either they endure the same destiny together with them,
or commit suicide: nor hitherto, in the memory of men, has there been
found any one who, upon his being slain to whose friendship he had
devoted himself, refused to die); Adcantuannus, [I say] endeavouring to
make a sally with these, when our soldiers had rushed together to arms,
upon a shout being raised at that part of the fortification, and a
fierce battle had been fought there, was driven back into the town, yet
he obtained from Crassus [the indulgence] that he should enjoy the same
terms of surrender [as the other inhabitants].</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIII">XXIII.--Crassus, having received their arms and hostages, marched into
the territories of the Vocates and the Tarusates. But then, the
barbarians being alarmed, because they had heard that a town fortified
by the nature of the place and by art had been taken by us in a few days
after our arrival there, began to send ambassadors into all quarters, to
combine, to give hostages one to another, to raise troops. Ambassadors
also are sent to those states of Hither <place region="spain">Spain</place> which are nearest to
<place region="aquitania">Aquitania</place>, and auxiliaries and leaders are summoned from them; on whose
arrival they proceed to carry on the war with great confidence, and with
a great host of men. They who had been with Q. Sertorius the whole
period [of his war in <place region="spain">Spain</place>] and were supposed to have very great skill
in military matters, are chosen leaders. These, adopting the practice of
the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, begin to select [advantageous] places, to fortify
their camp, to cut off our men from provisions, which, when Crassus
observes, [and likewise] that his forces, on account of their small
number, could not safely be separated; that the enemy both made
excursions and beset the passes, and [yet] left sufficient guard for
their camp; that on that account, corn and provision could not very
conveniently be brought up to him, and that the number of the enemy was
daily increased, he thought that he ought not to delay in giving battle.
This matter being brought to a council, when he discovered that all
thought the same thing, he appointed the next day for the fight.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIV">XXIV.--Having drawn out all his forces at the break of day, and
marshalled them in a double line, he posted the auxiliaries in the
centre, and waited to see what measures the enemy would take. They,
although on account of their great number and their ancient renown in
war, and the small number of our men, they supposed they might safely
fight, nevertheless considered it safer to gain the victory without any
wound, by besetting the passes [and] cutting off the provisions: and if
the Romans, on account of the want of corn, should begin to retreat,
they intended to attack them while encumbered in their march and
depressed in spirit [as being assailed while] under baggage. This
measure being approved of by the leaders and the forces of the Romans
drawn out, the enemy [still] kept themselves in their camp. Crassus
having remarked this circumstance, since the enemy, intimidated by their
own delay, and by the reputation [_i.e._ for cowardice arising thence]
had rendered our soldiers more eager for fighting, and the remarks of
all were heard [declaring] that no longer ought delay to be made in
going to the camp, after encouraging his men, he marches to the camp of
the enemy, to the great gratification of his own troops.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXV">XXV.--There, while some were filling up the ditch, and others, by
throwing a large number of darts, were driving the defenders from the
rampart and fortifications, and the auxiliaries, on whom Crassus did not
much rely in the battle, by supplying stones and weapons [to the
soldiers], and by conveying turf to the mound, presented the appearance
and character of men engaged in fighting; while also the enemy were
fighting resolutely and boldly, and their weapons, discharged from their
higher position, fell with great effect; the horse, having gone round
the camp of the enemy, reported to Crassus that the camp was not
fortified with equal care on the side of the Decuman gate, and had an
easy approach.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVI">XXVI.--Crassus, having exhorted the commanders of the horse to animate
their men by great rewards and promises, points out to them what he
wished to have done. They, as they had been commanded, having brought
out the four cohorts, which, as they had been left as a guard for the
camp, were not fatigued by exertion, and having led them round by a
somewhat longer way, lest they could be seen from the camp of the enemy,
when the eyes and minds of all were intent upon the battle, quickly
arrived at those fortifications which we have spoken of, and, having
demolished these, stood in the camp of the enemy before they were seen
by them, or it was known what was going on. And then, a shout being
heard in that quarter, our men, their strength having been recruited
(which usually occurs on the hope of victory), began to fight more
vigorously. The enemy, surrounded on all sides, [and] all their affairs
being despaired of, made great attempts to cast themselves down over the
ramparts and to seek safety in flight. These the cavalry pursued over
the very open plains, and after leaving scarcely a fourth part out of
the number of 50,000, which it was certain had assembled out of
<place region="aquitania">Aquitania</place> and from the Cantabri, returned late at night to the camp.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVII">XXVII.--Having heard of this battle, the greatest part of <place region="aquitania">Aquitania</place>
surrendered itself to Crassus, and of its own accord sent hostages, in
which number were the Tarbelli, the Bigerriones, the Preciani, the
Vocasates, the Tarusates, the Elurates, the Garites, the Ausci, the
Garumni, the Sibuzates, the Cocosates. A few [and those] most remote
nations, relying on the time of the year, because winter was at hand,
neglected to do this.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVIII">XXVIII.--About the same time <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, although the summer was nearly
past, yet since, all <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> being reduced, the Morini and the Menapii
alone remained in arms, and had never sent ambassadors to him [to make a
treaty] of peace, speedily led his army thither, thinking that that war
might soon be terminated. They resolved to conduct the war on a very
different method from the rest of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>; for as they perceived that
the greatest nations [of Gaul] who had engaged in war, had been routed
and overcome, and as they possessed continuous ranges of forests and
morasses, they removed themselves and all their property thither. When
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had arrived at the opening of these forests, and had begun to
fortify his camp, and no enemy was in the meantime seen, while our men
were dispersed on their respective duties, they suddenly rushed out from
all parts of the forest, and made an attack on our men. The latter
quickly took up arms and drove them back again to their forests; and
having killed a great many, lost a few of their own men while pursuing
them too far through those intricate places.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIX">XXIX.--During the remaining days after this, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> began to cut down
the forests; and that no attack might be made on the flank of the
soldiers, while unarmed and not foreseeing it, he placed together
(opposite to the enemy) all that timber which was cut down, and piled it
up as a rampart on either flank. When a great space had been, with
incredible speed, cleared in a few days, when the cattle [of the enemy]
and the rear of their baggage-train were already seized by our men, and
they themselves were seeking for the thickest parts of the forests,
storms of such a kind came on that the work was necessarily suspended,
and, through the continuance of the rains, the soldiers could not any
longer remain in their tents. Therefore, having laid waste all their
country, [and] having burnt their villages and houses, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> led back
his army and stationed them in winter-quarters among the Aulerci and
Lexovii, and the other states which had made war upon him last.</chapter></book>



<book num="4"><heading>BOOK IV></heading>

<chapter n="I">I.--The following winter (this was the year in which Cn. Pompey and M.
Crassus were consuls), those <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> [called] the Usipetes, and likewise
the Tenchtheri, with a great number of men, crossed the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, not far
from the place at which that river discharges itself into the sea. The
motive for crossing [that river] was that, having been for several years
harassed by the Suevi, they were constantly engaged in war, and hindered
from the pursuits of agriculture. The nation of the Suevi is by far the
largest and the most warlike nation of all the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>. They are said to
possess a hundred cantons, from each of which they yearly send from
their territories for the purpose of war a thousand armed men: the
others who remain at home, maintain [both] themselves and those engaged
in the expedition. The latter again, in their turn, are in arms the year
after: the former remain at home. Thus neither husbandry nor the art and
practice of war are neglected. But among them there exists no private
and separate land; nor are they permitted to remain more than one year
in one place for the purpose of residence. They do not live much on
corn, but subsist for the most part on milk and flesh, and are much
[engaged] in hunting; which circumstance must, by the nature of their
food, and by their daily exercise and the freedom of their life (for
having from boyhood been accustomed to no employment, or discipline,
they do nothing at all contrary to their inclination), both promote
their strength and render them men of vast stature of body. And to such
a habit have they brought themselves, that even in the coldest parts
they wear no clothing whatever except skins, by reason of the scantiness
of which a great portion of their body is bare, and besides they bathe
in open rivers.</chapter>

<chapter n="II">II.--Merchants have access to them rather that they may have persons to
whom they may sell those things which they have taken in war, than
because they need any commodity to be imported to them. Moreover, even
as to labouring cattle, in which the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> take the greatest pleasure,
and which they procure at a great price, the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> do not employ such
as are imported, but those poor and ill-shaped animals which belong to
their country; these, however, they render capable of the greatest
labour by daily exercise. In cavalry actions they frequently leap from
their horses and fight on foot; and train their horses to stand still in
the very spot on which they leave them, to which they retreat with great
activity when there is occasion; nor, according to their practice, is
anything regarded as more unseemly, or more unmanly, than to use
housings. Accordingly, they have the courage, though they be themselves
but few, to advance against any number whatever of horse mounted with
housings. They on no account permit wine to be imported to them, because
they consider that men degenerate in their powers of enduring fatigue,
and are rendered effeminate by that commodity.</chapter>

<chapter n="III">III.--They esteem it their greatest praise as a nation that the lands
about their territories lie unoccupied to a very great extent, inasmuch
as [they think] that by this circumstance is indicated that a great
number of nations cannot, withstand their power; and thus on one side of
the Suevi the lands are said to lie desolate for about six hundred
miles. On the other side they border on the Ubii, whose state was large
and flourishing, considering the condition of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, and who are
somewhat more refined than those of the same race and the rest [of the
<tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>], and that because they border on the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, and are much
resorted to by merchants, and are accustomed to the manners of the
<tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, by reason of their approximity to them. Though the Suevi, after
making the attempt frequently and in several wars, could not expel this
nation from their territories, on account of the extent and population
of their state, yet they made them tributaries, and rendered them less
distinguished and powerful [than they had ever been].</chapter>

<chapter n="IV">IV.--In the same condition were the Usipetes and the Tenchtheri (whom we
have mentioned above), who for many years resisted the power of the
Suevi, but being at last driven from their possessions, and having
wandered through many parts of Germany, came to the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, to districts
which the Menapii inhabited, and where they had lands, houses, and
villages on either side of the river. The latter people, alarmed by the
arrival of so great a multitude, removed from those houses which they
had on the other side of the river, and having placed guards on this
side the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, proceeded to hinder the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> from crossing. They,
finding themselves, after they had tried all means, unable either to
force a passage on account of their deficiency in shipping, or cross by
stealth on account of the guards of the Menapii, pretended to return to
their own settlements and districts; and, after having proceeded three
days' march, returned; and their cavalry having performed the whole of
this journey in one night, cut off the Menapii, who were ignorant of,
and did not expect [their approach, and] who, having moreover been
informed of the departure of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> by their scouts, had without
apprehension returned to their villages beyond the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>. Having slain
these, and seized their ships, they crossed the river before that part
of the Menapii, who were at peace in their settlements over the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>,
were apprised of [their intention]; and seizing all their houses,
maintained themselves upon their provisions during the rest of the
winter.</chapter>

<chapter n="V">V.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, when informed of these matters, fearing the fickle
disposition of the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, who are easily prompted to take up
resolutions, and much addicted to change, considered that nothing was to
be entrusted to them; for it is the custom of that people to compel
travellers to stop, even against their inclination, and inquire what
they may have heard, or may know, respecting any matter; and in towns
the common people throng around merchants and force them to state from
what countries they come, and what affairs they know of there. They
often engage in resolutions concerning the most important matters,
induced by these reports and stories alone; of which they must
necessarily instantly repent, since they yield to mere unauthorised
reports; and since most people give to their questions answers framed
agreeably to their wishes.</chapter>

<chapter n="VI">VI.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, being aware of their custom, in order that he might not
encounter a more formidable war, sets forward to the army earlier in the
year than he was accustomed to do. When he had arrived there, he
discovered that those things, which he had suspected would occur, had
taken place; that embassies had been sent to the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> by some of the
states, and that they had been entreated to leave the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, and had
been promised that all things which they desired should be provided by
the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>. Allured by this hope, the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> were then making excursions
to greater distances, and had advanced to the territories of the
Eburones and the Condrusi, who are under the protection of the Treviri.
After summoning the chiefs of <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> thought proper to pretend
ignorance of the things which he had discovered; and having conciliated
and confirmed their minds, and ordered some cavalry to be raised,
resolved to make war against the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>.</chapter>

<chapter n="VII">VII.--Having provided corn and selected his cavalry, he began to direct
his march towards those parts in which he heard the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> were. When
he was distant from them only a few days' march, ambassadors come to him
from their state; whose speech was as follows:--"That the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>
neither make war upon the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> first, nor do they decline, if
they are provoked, to engage with them in arms; for that this was the
custom of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> handed down to them from their forefathers, to
resist whatsoever people make war upon them and not to avert it by
entreaty; this, however, they confessed,--that they had come hither
reluctantly, having been expelled from their country. If the Romans were
disposed to accept their friendship, they might be serviceable allies to
them; and let them either assign them lands, or permit them to retain
those which they had acquired by their arms; that they are inferior to
the Suevi alone, to whom not even the immortal gods can show themselves
equal; that there was none at all besides on earth whom they could not
conquer."</chapter>

<chapter n="VIII">VIII.--To these remarks <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> replied in such terms as he thought
proper; but the conclusion of his speech was, "That he could make no
alliance with them, if they continued in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>; that it was not probable
that they who were not able to defend their own territories, should get
possession of those of others, nor were there any lands lying waste in
<place region="gaul">Gaul</place> which could be given away, especially to so great a number of men,
without doing wrong [to others]; but they might, if they were desirous,
settle in the territories of the Ubii; whose ambassadors were then with
him, and were complaining of the aggressions of the Suevi, and
requesting assistance from him; and that he would obtain this request
from them."</chapter>

<chapter n="IX">IX.--The ambassadors said that they would report these things to their
countrymen; and, after having deliberated on the matter, would return to
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> after the third day, they begged that he would not in the
meantime advance his camp nearer to them. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> said that he could not
grant them even that; for he had learned that they had sent a great part
of their cavalry over the Meuse to the Ambivariti, some days before, for
the purpose of plundering and procuring forage. He supposed that they
were then waiting for these horse, and that the delay was caused on this
account.</chapter>

<chapter n="X">X.--The Meuse rises from mount Le Vosge, which is in the territories of
the <tribe name="Lingones">Lingones</tribe>; and, having received a branch of the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, which is
called the Waal, forms the island of the Batavi, and not more than
eighty miles from it it falls into the ocean. But the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place> takes its
course among the <tribe name="lepontii">Lepontii</tribe>, who inhabit the <place mountain="Alps">Alps</place>, and is carried with a
rapid current for a long distance through the territories of the
Sarunates, <tribe name="helvetii">Helvetii</tribe>, <tribe name="sequani">Sequani</tribe>, Mediomatrici, Tribuci, and Treviri, and
when it approaches the ocean, divides into several branches; and, having
formed many and extensive islands, a great part of which are inhabited
by savage and barbarous nations (of whom there are some who are supposed
to live on fish and the eggs of sea-fowl), flows into the ocean by
several mouths.</chapter>

<chapter n="XI">XI.--When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> was not more than twelve miles distant from the enemy,
the ambassadors return to him, as had been arranged; who meeting him on
the march, earnestly entreated him not to advance any farther. When they
could not obtain this, they begged him to send on a despatch to those
who had marched in advance of the main army, and forbid them to engage;
and grant them permission to send ambassadors to the Ubii, and if the
princes and senate of the latter would give them security by oath, they
assured <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> that they would accept such conditions as might be
proposed by him; and requested that he would give them the space of
three days for negotiating these affairs. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> thought that these
things tended to the self-same point [as their other proposal]; [namely]
that, in consequence of a delay of three days intervening, their horse
which were at a distance might return; however, he said, that he would
not that day advance farther than four miles for the purpose of
procuring water; he ordered that they should assemble at that place in
as large a number as possible the following day, that he might inquire
into their demands. In the meantime he sends messengers to the officers
who had marched in advance with all the cavalry to order them not to
provoke the enemy to an engagement, and if they themselves were
assailed, to sustain the attack until he came up with the army.</chapter>

<chapter n="XII">XII.--But the enemy, as soon as they saw our horse, the number of which
was 5000, whereas they themselves had not more than 800 horse, because
those which had gone over the Meuse for the purpose of foraging had not
returned, while our men had no apprehensions, because their ambassadors
had gone away from <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> a little before, and that day had been
requested by them as a period of truce, made an onset on our men, and
soon threw them into disorder. When our men, in their turn, made a
stand, they, according to their practice, leaped from their horses to
their feet, and stabbing our horses in the belly and overthrowing a
great many of our men, put the rest to flight, and drove them forward so
much alarmed that they did not desist from their retreat till they had
come in sight of our army. In that encounter seventy-four of our horse
were slain; among them, Piso, an <place region="aquitania">Aquitania</place>n, a most valiant man, and
descended from a very illustrious family; whose grandfather had held the
sovereignty of his state, and had been styled friend by our senate. He,
while he was endeavouring to render assistance to his brother who was
surrounded by the enemy, and whom he rescued from danger, was himself
thrown from his horse, which was wounded under him, but still opposed
[his antagonists] with the greatest intrepidity, as long as he was able
to maintain the conflict. When at length he fell, surrounded on all
sides and after receiving many wounds, and his brother, who had then
retired from the fight, observed it from a distance, he spurred on his
horse, threw himself upon the enemy, and was killed.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIII">XIII.--After this engagement, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> considered that neither ought
ambassadors to be received to audience, nor conditions be accepted by
him from those who, after having sued for peace by way of stratagem and
treachery, had made war without provocation. And to wait till the
enemy's forces were augmented and their cavalry had returned, he
concluded, would be the greatest madness; and knowing the fickleness of
the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, he felt how much influence the enemy had already acquired
among them by this one skirmish. He [therefore] deemed that no time for
converting measures ought to be afforded them. After having resolved on
these things and communicated his plans to his lieutenants and quaestor
in order that he might not suffer any opportunity for engaging to escape
him, a very seasonable event occurred, namely, that on the morning of
the next day, a large body of <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, consisting of their princes and
old men, came to the camp to him to practise the same treachery and
dissimulation; but, as they asserted, for the purpose of acquitting
themselves for having engaged in a skirmish the day before, contrary to
what had been agreed and to what, indeed, they themselves had requested;
and also if they could by any means obtain a truce by deceiving him.
<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, rejoicing that they had fallen into his power, ordered them to
be detained. He then drew all his forces out of the camp, and commanded
the cavalry, because he thought they were intimidated by the late
skirmish, to follow in the rear.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIV">XIV.--Having marshalled his army in three lines, and in a short time
performed a march of eight miles, he arrived at the camp of the enemy
before the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> could perceive what was going on; who being suddenly
alarmed by all the circumstances, both by the speediness of our arrival
and the absence of their own officers, as time was afforded neither for
concerting measures nor for seizing their arms, are perplexed as to
whether it would be better to lead out their forces against the enemy,
or to defend their camp, or seek their safety by flight. Their
consternation being made apparent by their noise and tumult, our
soldiers, excited by the treachery of the preceding day, rushed into the
camp: such of them as could readily get their arms for a short time
withstood our men, and gave battle among their carts and baggage-waggons;
but the rest of the people, [consisting] of boys and women (for they had
left their country and crossed the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place> with all their families), began
to fly in all directions; in pursuit of whom <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> sent the cavalry.</chapter>

<chapter n="XV">XV.--The <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> when, upon hearing a noise behind them, [they looked
and] saw that their families were being slain, throwing away their arms
and abandoning their standards, fled out of the camp, and when they had
arrived at the confluence of the Meuse and the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, the survivors
despairing of farther escape, as a great number of their countrymen had
been killed, threw themselves into the river and there perished,
overcome by fear, fatigue, and the violence of the stream. Our soldiers,
after the alarm of so great a war, for the number of the enemy amounted
to 430,000, returned to their camp, all safe to a man, very few being
even wounded. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> granted those whom he had detained in the camp
liberty of departing. They however, dreading revenge and torture from
the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>, whose lands they had harassed, said that they desired to
remain with him. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> granted them permission.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVI">XVI.--The German war being finished, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> thought it expedient for him
to cross the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, for many reasons; of which this was the most
weighty, that, since he saw the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> were so easily urged to go into
<place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, he desired they should have their fears for their own territories
when they discovered that the army of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe> both could and
dared pass the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>. There was added also, that that portion of the
cavalry of the Usipetes and the Tenchtheri, which I have above related
to have crossed the Meuse for the purpose of plundering and procuring
forage, and was not present at the engagement, had betaken themselves,
after the retreat of their countrymen, across the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place> into the
territories of the Sigambri, and united themselves to them. When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>
sent ambassadors to them, to demand that they should give up to him
those who had made war against him and against <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, they replied, "That
the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place> bounded the empire of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>; if he did not think it
just for the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe> to pass over into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> against his consent, why did
he claim that anything beyond the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place> should be subject to his
dominion or power?" The Ubii also, who alone, out of all the nations
lying beyond the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, had sent ambassadors to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, and formed an
alliance and given hostages, earnestly entreated "that he would bring
them assistance, because they were grievously oppressed by the Suevi;
or, if he was prevented from doing so by the business of the
commonwealth, he would at least transport his army over the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>; that
that would be sufficient for their present assistance and their hope for
the future; that so great was the name and the reputation of his army,
even among the most remote nations of the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, arising from the
defeat of Ariovistus and this last battle which was fought, that they
might be safe under the fame and friendship of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>." They
promised a large number of ships for transporting the army.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVII">XVII.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, for those reasons which I have mentioned, had resolved to
cross the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>; but to cross by ships he neither deemed to be
sufficiently safe, nor considered consistent with his own dignity or
that of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>. Therefore, although the greatest difficulty in
forming a bridge was presented to him, on account of the breadth,
rapidity, and depth of the river, he nevertheless considered that it
ought to be attempted by him, or that his army ought not otherwise to be
led over. He devised this plan of a bridge. He joined together at the
distance of two feet, two piles, each a foot and a half thick, sharpened
a little at the lower end, and proportioned in length to the depth of
the river. After he had, by means of engines, sunk these into the river,
and fixed them at the bottom, and then driven them in with rammers, not
quite perpendicularly, like a stake, but bending forward and sloping, so
as to incline in the direction of the current of the river; he also
placed two [other piles] opposite to these, at the distance of forty
feet lower down, fastened together in the same manner, but directed
against the force and current of the river. Both these, moreover, were
kept firmly apart by beams two feet thick (the space which the binding
of the piles occupied), laid in at their extremities between two braces
on each side; and in consequence of these being in different directions
and fastened on sides the one opposite to the other, so great was the
strength of the work, and such the arrangement of the materials, that in
proportion as the greater body of water dashed against the bridge, so
much the closer were its parts held fastened together. These beams were
bound together by timber laid over them in the direction of the length
of the bridge, and were [then] covered over with laths and hurdles; and
in addition to this, piles were driven into the water obliquely, at the
lower side of the bridge, and these serving as buttresses, and being
connected with every portion of the work, sustained the force of the
stream: and there were others also above the bridge, at a moderate
distance; that if trunks of trees or vessels were floated down the river
by the barbarians for the purpose of destroying the work, the violence
of such things might be diminished by these defences, and might not
injure the bridge.</chapter>

<chapter n="XVIII">XVIII.--Within ten days after the timber began to be collected, the
whole work was completed, and the whole army led over. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, leaving a
strong guard at each end of the bridge, hastens into the territories of
the Sigambri. In the meantime ambassadors from several nations come to
him, whom, on their suing for peace and alliance, he answers in a
courteous manner, and orders hostages to be brought to him. But the
Sigambri, at the very time the bridge was begun to be built, made
preparations for a flight (by the advice of such of the Tenchtheri and
Usipetes as they had amongst them), and quitted their territories and
conveyed away all their possessions, and concealed themselves in deserts
and woods.</chapter>

<chapter n="XIX">XIX.--<persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, having remained in their territories a few days, and burnt
all their villages and houses, and cut down their corn, proceeded into
the territories of the Ubii; and having promised them his assistance, if
they were ever harassed by the Suevi, he learned from them these
particulars: that the Suevi, after they had by means of their scouts
found that the bridge was being built, had called a council, according
to their custom, and sent orders to all parts of their state to remove
from the towns and convey their children, wives, and all their
possessions into the woods, and that all who could bear arms should
assemble in one place; that the place thus chosen was nearly the centre
of those regions which the Suevi possessed; that in this spot they had
resolved to await the arrival of the Romans, and give them battle there.
When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> discovered this, having already accomplished all those
things on account of which he had resolved to lead his army over,
namely, to strike fear into the <tribe name="germans">Germans</tribe>, take vengeance on the Sigambri,
and free the Ubii from the invasion of the Suevi, having spent
altogether eighteen days beyond the <place river="rhine">Rhine</place>, and thinking he had advanced
far enough to serve both honour and interest, he returned into <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>, and
cut down the bridge.</chapter>

<chapter n="XX">XX.--During the short part of summer which remained, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, although in
these countries, as all <place region="gaul">Gaul</place> lies towards the north, the winters are
early, nevertheless resolved to proceed into Britain, because he
discovered that in almost all the wars with the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe> succours had been
furnished to our enemy from that country; and even if the time of year
should be insufficient for carrying on the war, yet he thought it would
be of great service to him if he only entered the island, and saw into
the character of the people, and got knowledge of their localities,
harbours, and landing-places, all which were for the most part unknown
to the <tribe name="gauls">Gauls</tribe>. For neither does any one except merchants generally go
thither, nor even to them was any portion of it known, except the
sea-coast and those parts which are opposite to <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>. Therefore, after
having called up to him the merchants from all parts, he could learn
neither what was the size of the island, nor what or how numerous were
the nations which inhabited it, nor what system of war they followed,
nor what customs they used, nor what harbours were convenient for a
great number of large ships.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXI">XXI.--He sends before him Caius Volusenus with a ship of war, to acquire
a knowledge of these particulars before he in person should make a
descent into the island, as he was convinced that this was a judicious
measure. He commissioned him to thoroughly examine into all matters, and
then return to him as soon as possible. He himself proceeds to the
Morini with all his forces. He orders ships from all parts of the
neighbouring countries, and the fleet which the preceding summer he had
built for the war with the Veneti, to assemble in this place. In the
meantime, his purpose having been discovered, and reported to the
Britons by merchants, ambassadors come to him from several states of the
island, to promise that they will give hostages, and submit to the
government of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>. Having given them an audience, he after
promising liberally, and exhorting them to continue in that purpose,
sends them back to their own country, and [despatches] with them
Commius, whom, upon subduing the Atrebates, he had created king there, a
man whose courage and conduct he esteemed, and who he thought would be
faithful to him, and whose influence ranked highly in those countries.
He orders him to visit as many states as he could, and persuade them to
embrace the protection of the <tribe name="romans">Roman people</tribe>, and apprise them that he
would shortly come thither. Volusenus, having viewed the localities as
far as means could be afforded one who dared not leave his ship and
trust himself to barbarians, returns to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> on the fifth day, and
reports what he had there observed.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXII">XXII.--While <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> remains in these parts for the purpose of procuring
ships, ambassadors come to him from a great portion of the Morini, to
plead their excuse respecting their conduct on the late occasion;
alleging that it was as men uncivilised, and as those who were
unacquainted with our custom, that they had made war upon the Roman
people, and promising to perform what he should command. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>,
thinking that this had happened fortunately enough for him, because he
neither wished to leave an enemy behind him, nor had an opportunity for
carrying on a war, by reason of the time of year, nor considered that
employment in such trifling matters was to be preferred to his
enterprise on Britain, imposes a large number of hostages; and when
these were brought, he received them to his protection. Having collected
together and provided about eighty transport ships, as many as he
thought necessary for conveying over two legions, he assigned such
[ships] of war as he had besides to the quaestor, his lieutenants, and
officers of cavalry. There were in addition to these eighteen ships of
burden which were prevented, eight miles from that place, by winds, from
being able to reach the same port. These he distributed amongst the
horse; the rest of the army he delivered to Q. Titurius Sabinus and L.
Aurunculeius Cotta, his lieutenants, to lead into the territories of the
Menapii and those cantons of the Morini from which ambassadors had not
come to him. He ordered P. Sulpicius Rufus, his lieutenant, to hold
possession of the harbour, with such a garrison as he thought
sufficient.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIII">XXIII.--These matters being arranged, finding the weather favourable for
his voyage, he set sail about the third watch, and ordered the horse to
march forward to the farther port, and there embark and follow him. As
this was performed rather tardily by them, he himself reached Britain
with the first squadron of ships, about the fourth hour of the day, and
there saw the forces of the enemy drawn up in arms on all the hills. The
nature of the place was this: the sea was confined by mountains so close
to it that a dart could be thrown from their summit upon the shore.
Considering this by no means a fit place for disembarking, he remained
at anchor till the ninth hour, for the other ships to arrive there.
Having in the meantime assembled the lieutenants and military tribunes,
he told them both what he had learnt from Volusenus, and what he wished
to be done; and enjoined them (as the principle of military matters, and
especially as maritime affairs, which have a precipitate and uncertain
action, required) that all things should be performed by them at a nod
and at the instant. Having dismissed them, meeting both with wind and
tide favourable at the same time, the signal being given and the anchor
weighed, he advanced about seven miles from that place, and stationed
his fleet over against an open and level shore.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIV">XXIV.--But the barbarians, upon perceiving the design of the Romans,
sent forward their cavalry and charioteers, a class of warriors of whom
it is their practice to make great use in their battles, and following
with the rest of their forces, endeavoured to prevent our men landing.
In this was the greatest difficulty, for the following reasons, namely,
because our ships, on account of their great size, could be stationed
only in deep water; and our soldiers, in places unknown to them, with
their hands embarrassed, oppressed with a large and heavy weight of
armour, had at the same time to leap from the ships, stand amidst the
waves, and encounter the enemy; whereas they, either on dry ground, or
advancing a little way into the water, free in all their limbs, in
places thoroughly known to them, could confidently throw their weapons
and spur on their horses, which were accustomed to this kind of service.
Dismayed by these circumstances and altogether untrained in this mode of
battle, our men did not all exert the same vigour and eagerness which
they had been wont to exert in engagements on dry ground.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXV">XXV.--When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> observed this, he ordered the ships of war, the
appearance of which was somewhat strange to the barbarians and the
motion more ready for service, to be withdrawn a little from the
transport vessels, and to be propelled by their oars, and be stationed
towards the open flank of the enemy, and the enemy to be beaten off and
driven away with slings, arrows, and engines: which plan was of great
service to our men; for the barbarians being startled by the form of our
ships and the motions of our oars and the nature of our engines, which
was strange to them, stopped, and shortly after retreated a little. And
while our men were hesitating [whether they should advance to the
shore], chiefly on account of the depth of the sea, he who carried the
eagle of the tenth legion, after supplicating the gods that the matter
might turn out favourably to the legion, exclaimed, "Leap, fellow
soldiers, unless you wish to betray your eagle to the enemy. I, for my
part, will perform my duty to the commonwealth and my general." When he
had said this with a loud voice, he leaped from the ship and proceeded
to bear the eagle toward the enemy. Then our men, exhorting one another
that so great a disgrace should not be incurred, all leaped from the
ship. When those in the nearest vessels saw them, they speedily followed
and approached the enemy.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVI">XXVI.--The battle was maintained vigorously on both sides. Our men,
however, as they could neither keep their ranks, nor get firm footing,
nor follow their standards, and as one from one ship and another from
another assembled around whatever standards they met, were thrown into
great confusion. But the enemy, who were acquainted with all the
shallows, when from the shore they saw any coming from a ship one by
one, spurred on their horses, and attacked them while embarrassed; many
surrounded a few, others threw their weapons upon our collected forces
on their exposed flank. When <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> observed this, he ordered the boats
of the ships of war and the spy sloops to be filled with soldiers, and
sent them up to the succour of those whom he had observed in distress.
Our men, as soon as they made good their footing on dry ground, and all
their comrades had joined them, made an attack upon the enemy, and put
them to flight, but could not pursue them very far, because the horse
had not been able to maintain their course at sea and reach the island.
This alone was wanting to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s accustomed success.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVII">XXVII.--The enemy being thus vanquished in battle, as soon as they
recovered after their flight, instantly sent ambassadors to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> to
negotiate about peace. They promised to give hostages and perform what
he should command. Together with these ambassadors came Commius the
Atrebatian, who, as I have above said, had been sent by <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> into
Britain. Him they had seized upon when leaving his ship, although in the
character of ambassador he bore the general's commission to them, and
thrown into chains: then after the battle was fought, they sent him
back, and in suing for peace cast the blame of that act upon the common
people, and entreated that it might be pardoned on account of their
indiscretion. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, complaining that after they had sued for peace,
and had voluntarily sent ambassadors into the continent for that
purpose, they had made war without a reason, said that he would pardon
their indiscretion, and imposed hostages, a part of whom they gave
immediately; the rest they said they would give in a few days, since
they were sent for from remote places. In the meantime they ordered
their people to return to the country parts, and the chiefs assembled
from all quarters, and proceeded to surrender themselves and their
states to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXVIII">XXVIII.--A peace being established by these proceedings four days after
we had come into Britain, the eighteen ships, to which reference has
been made above, and which conveyed the cavalry, set sail from the upper
port with a gentle gale; when, however, they were approaching Britain
and were seen from the camp, so great a storm suddenly arose that none
of them could maintain their course at sea; and some were taken back to
the same port from which they had started;--others, to their great
danger, were driven to the lower part of the island, nearer to the west;
which, however, after having cast anchor, as they were getting filled
with water, put out to sea through necessity in a stormy night, and made
for the continent.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXIX">XXIX.--It happened that night to be full moon, which usually occasions
very high tides in that ocean; and that circumstance was unknown to our
men. Thus, at the same time, the tide began to fill the ships of war
which <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had provided to convey over his army, and which he had
drawn up on the strand; and the storm began to dash the ships of burden
which were riding at anchor against each other; nor was any means
afforded our men of either managing them or of rendering any service. A
great many ships having been wrecked, inasmuch as the rest, having lost
their cables, anchors, and other tackling, were unfit for sailing, a
great confusion, as would necessarily happen, arose throughout the army;
for there were no other ships in which they could be conveyed back, and
all things which are of service in repairing vessels were wanting, and
corn for the winter had not been provided in those places, because it
was understood by all that they would certainly winter in <place region="gaul">Gaul</place>.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXX">XXX.--On discovering these things the chiefs of Britain, who had come up
after the battle was fought to perform those conditions which <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had
imposed, held a conference, when they perceived that cavalry, and ships,
and corn were wanting to the Romans, and discovered the small number of
our soldiers from the small extent of the camp (which, too, was on this
account more limited than ordinary because <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> had conveyed over his
legions without baggage), and thought that the best plan was to renew
the war, and cut off our men from corn and provisions and protract the
affair till winter; because they felt confident that, if they were
vanquished or cut off from a return, no one would afterwards pass over
into Britain for the purpose of making war. Therefore, again entering
into a conspiracy, they began to depart from the camp by degrees and
secretly bring up their people from the country parts.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXI">XXXI.--But <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>, although he had not as yet discovered their measures,
yet, both from what had occurred to his ships, and from the circumstance
that they had neglected to give the promised hostages, suspected that
the thing would come to pass which really did happen. He therefore
provided remedies against all contingencies; for he daily conveyed corn
from the country parts into the camp, used the timber and brass of such
ships as were most seriously damaged for repairing the rest, and ordered
whatever things besides were necessary for this object to be brought to
him from the continent. And thus, since that business was executed by
the soldiers with the greatest energy, he effected that, after the loss
of twelve ships, a voyage could be made well enough in the rest.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXII">XXXII.--While these things are being transacted, one legion had been
sent to forage, according to custom, and no suspicion of war had arisen
as yet, and some of the people remained in the country parts, others
went backwards and forwards to the camp, they who were on duty at the
gates of the camp reported to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> that a greater dust than was usual
was seen in that direction in which the legion had marched. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>,
suspecting that which was [really the case],--that some new enterprise
was undertaken by the barbarians, ordered the two cohorts which were on
duty to march into that quarter with him, and two other cohorts to
relieve them on duty; the rest to be armed and follow him immediately.
When he had advanced some little way from the camp, he saw that his men
were overpowered by the enemy and scarcely able to stand their ground,
and that, the legion being crowded together, weapons were being cast on
them from all sides. For as all the corn was reaped in every part with
the exception of one, the enemy, suspecting that our men would repair to
that, had concealed themselves in the woods during the night. Then
attacking them suddenly, scattered as they were, and when they had laid
aside their arms, and were engaged in reaping, they killed a small
number, threw the rest into confusion, and surrounded them with their
cavalry and chariots.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXIII">XXXIII.--Their mode of fighting with their chariots is this: firstly,
they drive about in all directions and throw their weapons and generally
break the ranks of the enemy with the very dread of their horses and the
noise of their wheels; and when they have worked themselves in between
the troops of horse, leap from their chariots and engage on foot. The
charioteers in the meantime withdraw some little distance from the
battle, and so place themselves with the chariots that, if their masters
are overpowered by the number of the enemy, they may have a ready
retreat to their own troops. Thus they display in battle the speed of
horse, [together with] the firmness of infantry; and by daily practice
and exercise attain to such expertness that they are accustomed, even on
a declining and steep place, to check their horses at full speed, and
manage and turn them in an instant and run along the pole, and stand on
the yoke, and thence betake themselves with the greatest celerity to
their chariots again.

XXXIV.-Under these circumstances, our men being dismayed by the novelty
of this mode of battle, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> most seasonably brought assistance; for
upon his arrival the enemy paused, and our men recovered from their
fear; upon which, thinking the time unfavourable for provoking the enemy
and coming to an action, he kept himself in his own quarter, and, a
short time having intervened, drew back the legions into the camp. While
these things were going on, and all our men engaged, the rest of the
Britons, who were in the fields, departed. Storms then set in for
several successive days, which both confined our men to camp and
hindered the enemy from attacking us. In the meantime the barbarians
despatched messengers to all parts and reported to their people the
small number of our soldiers, and how good an opportunity was given for
obtaining spoil and for liberating themselves for ever, if they should
only drive the Romans from their camp. Having by these means speedily
got together a large force of infantry and of cavalry, they came up to
the camp.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXV">XXXV.--Although <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> anticipated that the same thing which had
happened on former occasions would then occur--that, if the enemy were
routed, they would escape from danger by their speed; still, having got
about thirty horse, which Commius the Atrebatian, of whom mention has
been made, had brought over with him [from Gaul], he drew up the legions
in order of battle before the camp. When the action commenced, the enemy
were unable to sustain the attack of our men long, and turned their
backs; our men pursued them as far as their speed and strength
permitted, and slew a great number of them; then, having destroyed and
burnt everything far and wide, they retreated to their camp.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXVI">XXXVI.--The same day, ambassadors sent by the enemy came to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> to
negotiate a peace. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> doubled the number of hostages which he had
before demanded; and ordered that they should be brought over to the
continent, because, since the time of the equinox was near, he did not
consider that, with his ships out of repair, the voyage ought to be
deferred till winter. Having met with favourable weather he set sail a
little after midnight, and all his fleet arrived safe at the continent,
except two of the ships of burden which could not make the same port
which the other ships did, and were carried a little lower down.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXVII">XXXVII.--When our soldiers, about 300 in number, had been drawn out of
these two ships, and were marching to the camp, the Morini, whom <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>,
when setting forth for Britain, had left in a state of peace, excited by
the hope of spoil, at first surrounded them with a small number of men,
and ordered them to lay down their arms, if they did not wish to be
slain; afterwards however, when they, forming a circle, stood on their
defence, a shout was raised and about 6000 of the enemy soon assembled;
which being reported, <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> sent all the cavalry in the camp as a
relief to his men. In the meantime our soldiers sustained the attack of
the enemy, and fought most valiantly for more than four hours, and,
receiving but few wounds themselves, slew several of them. But after our
cavalry came in sight, the enemy, throwing away their arms, turned their
backs, and a great number of them were killed.</chapter>

<chapter n="XXXVIII">XXXVIII.--The day following <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> sent Labienus, his lieutenant, with
those legions which he had brought back from Britain, against the
Morini, who had revolted; who, as they had no place to which they might
retreat, on account of the drying up of their marshes (which they had
availed themselves of as a place of refuge the preceding year), almost
all fell into the power of Labienus. In the meantime <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s
lieutenants, Q. Titurius and L. Cotta, who had led the legions into the
territories of the Menapii, having laid waste all their lands, cut down
their corn and burnt their houses, returned to <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName> because the
Menapii had all concealed themselves in their thickest woods. <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>
fixed the winter quarters of all the legions amongst the <tribe name="belgae">Belgae</tribe>. Thither
only two British states sent hostages; the rest omitted to do so. For
these successes, a thanksgiving of twenty days was decreed by the senate
upon receiving <persName eth="roman" role="general">Caesar</persName>'s letter.</chapter></book></section>

</root>